<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Medicina veterum vindicata, or, An answer to a book, entitled Medela medicinæ in which the ancient method and rules are defended ... / by John Twysden ...</title>
            <author>Twysden, John, 1607-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 224 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 120 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3547</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20872</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12177690</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12177690</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55561</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64060)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55561)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 901:48)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Medicina veterum vindicata, or, An answer to a book, entitled Medela medicinæ in which the ancient method and rules are defended ... / by John Twysden ...</title>
                  <author>Twysden, John, 1607-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 214, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.G. for John Crook ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nedham, Marchamont, 1620-1678. --  Medela medicinae.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55561:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55561:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicina Veterum vindicata:</hi> OR AN ANSWER To a Book, entituled <hi>Medela Medicinae;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which the ancient Method and Rules are defended, and farther ſhewed, that there is no ſuch change in the Diſeaſes of this Age, or their Nature in general, that we ſhould be obliged to an alteration of them.</p>
            <p>Againſt the Calumnies and bitter Invectives of an Author who calls himſelf <hi>M. N. Med. Londinenſ.</hi> but in his Epiſtle before a Book, put out by Mr. <hi>Bolneſt,</hi> gives himſelf the name of <hi>Mar. Nedham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Twyſden,</hi> Doctor of Phyſick, and one of the Fellows of the Kings College of Phyſicians in <hi>Lond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. G.</hi> for <hi>John Crook,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Ship</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:55561:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55561:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, <hi>Edward</hi> Earl of <hi>Clarendon,</hi> Lord High Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> Chancellor of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and one of His Majeſty's moſt Honorable Privy Council. AND To the Right Hon. Sir <hi>John Keeling,</hi> Knight, Lord Chief Juſtice of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Court of <hi>Kings-Bench.</hi> The Right Hon. Sir <hi>Orlando Bridgman,</hi> Knight and Baronet, Lord Chief Juſtice of His Majeſty's Court of <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas.</hi> To the Right Hon. Sir <hi>Matthew Hales,</hi> Knight, Lord Chief Baron of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Court of <hi>Exchequer:</hi> With all the reſt of the Judges and Barons of His Majeſty's Courts in <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>My</hi> Lord, <hi>and you, my</hi> Lords, <hi>the Judges,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BE pleaſed to give me leave to acquaint your Lordſhips, that I
<pb facs="tcp:55561:3"/>have not preſum'd to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this ſmall Tractate under ſo noble a Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, out of any worth I conceiv it can draw from the Author, but onely what it takes from the nobleneſs of the Subject, being the Profeſsion of Phyſick, a Profeſsion of late ſtruck at by many Writers, who have not made themſelves in any thing more famous then in their bold Calumnies againſt thoſe Rules and
<pb facs="tcp:55561:3"/>Method, which more learned men then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have for many Ages thought fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend unto Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Neither have they reſted here, but endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to draw His moſt Gracious Majeſty's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence to their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, and by that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous way of innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting through ſubſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Hands, laboured to erect a new Society of Chymical Phyſicians in
<pb facs="tcp:55561:4"/>
               <hi>London,</hi> in oppoſition to that Body already ſetled.</p>
            <p>'Tis certainly high time to fly to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips for protection, whoſe wiſedom is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning enough, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity always awake to do juſtice to our poor College, eſpecially when His Majeſty's Name is like to be traduced, their Liberties granted by His Charters, and confirmed by Acts of Parliament, in
<pb facs="tcp:55561:4"/>danger to be infringed, by introducing a Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in practiſing Phyſick by every one ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend himſelf able in that Faculty.</p>
            <p>I ſhall humbly caſt my ſelf and what I have written at your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips feet, being in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more ambitious then by any act of mine to expreſs the great Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour I have for all of your learned Profeſsion,
<pb facs="tcp:55561:5"/>and the ſervice I ſhall ever readily pay to your Perſons, who am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips <hi>Moſt humble Servant,</hi> JOHN TWYSDEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:55561:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T will not be amiſs to let the Reader un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that I had not put an end to the Anſwer of <hi>Medela Medicina,</hi> publiſhed by <hi>M. N.</hi> when there came to my hands a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, made publick by one <hi>Edward Bolneſt,</hi> called <hi>Medicina Inſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata,</hi> with an Epiſtolatary Diſcourſe prefixed by the Author of <hi>Medela Medicinae;</hi> at the end of this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle you have his name, <hi>Mar. Ned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham:</hi> ſo that we need no more gueſs at him who now owns the Name and Book. I have paſſed my cenſure upon the firſt, and hold it not unprofitable to the Reader to make ſome Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions upon the laſt. He begins with
<pb facs="tcp:55561:6"/>a commendation of thoſe noble Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, the virtues whereof the Author of that Treatiſe gives, as he ſaith, the world ſome account of; then commends his learning and ability, and from that one example concludes, that their Society are not a company of illiterate Profeſſors: 'twould indeed follow, that if there were one learned man among them, that they were not all illiterate; but, notwithſtanding, the Society might be unlearned, and, as perhaps it will be found, moſt of them very ignorant, for <hi>denominatio ſumitur à majore parte.</hi> But I had let this paſs had he not made uſe of this mans parts to upbraid thoſe, that are truly and deſervedly made Doctors in our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, by calling them in ſcorn their Worſhips, and Mr. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, telling us of ſtrange Cures every day performed by their party, with new Medicines and Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are left as incurable by <hi>Galenick</hi> remedies; things falſe
<pb facs="tcp:55561:6"/>and ridiculous, and with no wiſe man to gain credit, till upon a full in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the fact and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Medicine, it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the world to be new, and I believe it would then be found, that nothing is uſed by any of that gang but what hath been long enough known to others, and often practiſed with various ſucceſs. But 'tis with theſe men as with your common Fortune-tellers, who upon a good gueſs are cried up as rare Artiſts, when their numerous lies are not taken notice of. So one cure, after the application of any remedy by theſe men is by their own Trumpet blown about, whereas the many kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by their ignorance are not taken notice of. After ſome more vain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions againſt the unprofitable learning and idle pride of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Phyſick, and the Schola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick way of learning, which muſt needs ſtrike at all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities where 'tis profeſſed, as he doth at that
<pb facs="tcp:55561:7"/>Scarlet there given them as a badge of their honour, worthily acquired in thoſe places, interlarding his diſcourſe with diſgraceful ſpeeches againſt <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> whom he calls Dreamers, and a jeer or two againſt thoſe that were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Fellows of the <hi>King's Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of Phyſicians in <hi>London, in honorem,</hi> not conſidering, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſome glances at actions done by Collegiate Bodies, allowed by the Kings Charter, and eſtabliſhed in their Rights by Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, doth obliquely ſtrike at the Founder and Protectors of them: nor that thoſe preferred by us to that honour were perſons moſt of them of great deſert and knowledge in that Science they before made Profeſſion of, and many of them dignified with Honourary Titles from the King. He tells you of the great labour of him and his fellows to erect a new College, (which, by the way, yet lies in <hi>Utopia,</hi> or buried in the middle
<pb facs="tcp:55561:7"/>of the <hi>Atlantick</hi> Sea) to put people in a ready way of eaſe and ſecurity for their lives and purſes; aſſerting, that moſt of the Lords and Noble Gentlemen of learning prefer their way before the <hi>Galenick;</hi> and that therefore we cry up our ſelves alſo as Chymiſts, things very injurious to the whole body of the Nobility and Gentry, out of which I am confident they cannot pick ten Families that will venture their healths upon the practiſe of theſe Operators (as they call themſelves) by Fire, without the ſound adviſe and judgment of thoſe well skilled in the <hi>Dogmatick</hi> or <hi>Galenick</hi> way. 'Tis true, <hi>Gens humana eſt novitatis avida,</hi> ſome may be content to hear them talk and brag of their great feats in Phyſick, and perhaps to divert themſelves, ſee ſome Chymical operations which are delightful enough, and by theſe great boaſters commended in their effects above the truth. But let theſe men be touched with on acute ſickneſs, to
<pb facs="tcp:55561:8"/>whom will they then have recourſe I would gladly know? to theſe, many of them illiterate pretenders, or to others of ſound judgment and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding? Experience ſhews their practiſe lies generally among thoſe who frequent <hi>Mountebanks</hi> Stalls, who for ſix-pence will ſell them Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines to cure all diſeaſes. In the next place 'tis a wrong to thoſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians that are skilled, as many are, in Chymical operations, as if they made a pretence of that knowledge, becauſe they ſaw the other way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted; whereas with more reaſon he ought to believe their ſtudy and knowledge therein proceeded from their conſideration, that 'twas a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary part of that learning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to every Phyſician, yet not to make the other deſpiſed. From pu ting a ſcorn upon the <hi>Scholaſtick rode,</hi> deriding the Kings College of <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>ſlighting Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> leſt we might judge no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left praiſe-worthy, he falls into
<pb facs="tcp:55561:8"/>the commendation of himſelf and his fellow-writer; yet muſt that be uſher'd in with a contempt put upon the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, as well forein as our own, for their eaſineſs to confer Academick Honours upon unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers. He tells you they are <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity-men, and, no doubt, paying their Fees may bring their Formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to <hi>London. But that all Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demick Honours, and the Veniſon that helps to make them, are not worth the loſs of one afternoon in their Laboratory;</hi> where they are ſo employ'd, that they have not lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to croſs the Seas, and have the Proverb made good of them, <hi>Accipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Aurum, dimittimus Aſinum.</hi> 'Twill certainly be well for the world, when they ſhall ſee this great Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, now in expectation from their immenſe labours, brought under the Sickle. I wiſh it may not be verifi'd which is wittily ſaid by <hi>Minſichtus,</hi> in his <hi>Teſtamentum Hadrianeum, Stercoreum inveniet qui ſtercora
<pb facs="tcp:55561:9"/>ſeminat arvum:</hi> Sow dung, you ſhall reap muck. But in earneſt, Mr. <hi>Ned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> are you not to blame, that at once make all the world your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? is it not a ſtrange piece of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, that a ſon ſhould complain of the indulgence of his mother, when 'tis applied to himſelf? If <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties either at home or abroad have been too eaſie ſometime in conferring degrees, ſhall any one matriculated into that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity take a liberty to upbraid them for it? Does the reaſons of their actions always appear? Perhaps they may think, and juſtly, that ability in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of literature may be fitly rewarded with the Honours due to another Faculty. Perhaps they may diſcover ſomething that may promiſe a future progreſs worthy that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour they confer. But in truth, will it be found ſo eaſie? Let him go abroad, perhaps he will find himſelf deceived. I never knew any Degree conferred abroad without a previous
<pb facs="tcp:55561:9"/>examination, and rigid enough, if they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you intend to profeſs that Faculty you deſire to be promoted to. Let him then return and deſire admittance to the ſame Degree in his own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, when he hath paſſed the examination of the Profeſſor in Phyſick, the Vice-chancellor, and other Delegates appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for that Faculty, and has obtained Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficates from ſuch a number as is deſigned to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt they believe him fit to paſs; and after all this, ſhall then come to ſupplicate the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity for his Degree. Let him laſtly come to be admitted as a member of the College at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and paſs a three months examination by the Preſident and four Cenſors, and after this ſtand the teſt of all the Fellows met together, and perhaps he will not find his paſsage to that Degree, and the accumulations of it ſo very eaſie a matter to paſs through. Yet after all theſe unhandſom reflexions, both upon the men and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities which promoted them, we muſt believe he deſpiſeth not Academick Honours, <hi>nay, that ours are the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined in Europe, and deſerve all honour we can give them.</hi> This were pretty well from one that hath not leiſure to go to them. But we
<pb facs="tcp:55561:10"/>may obſerve (as 'tis ſaid of the <hi>Lamprey</hi>) a ſtring of poiſon runs through the body of theſe words. 'Tis a good flower in Rhetorick, often uſed by <hi>Tully</hi> in his Orations againſt <hi>Catiline, Anthony,</hi> and other, to reckon up the virtues, parts and abilities of them he means to deſtroy, that by laying to view what thoſe virtues ſhould have taught them to do, their vices might be more conſpicuous. <hi>Quos laudando maximè vituperat.</hi> The Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick Honours are not to be deſpiſed, ours are the moſt refined, more wary in diſtribution of Degrees. <hi>But ſtill the body of Practiſers are made up of titular things, foiſted up among Foreiners, or elſe by alliance at home, the favour or recommendation of ſome Father, or Unkle, or Couſin Doctor, that hath had a name, though perhaps little more of true knowledge in Medicine then the Novice he prefers.</hi> Great warineſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities to admit ſuch titular things, but whom hath he known by them or the College of <hi>London</hi> ſo admitted? Where is then that great body of Practiſers ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred? Perhaps he may reflect upon the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and their Chancellors, and their admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb facs="tcp:55561:10"/>of perſons to practiſe upon ſuch favour or commendation. If there be ſuch an abuſe by any of them, let them anſwer for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, upon examination I am confident no ſuch thing will be found. The other mean ways of promoting their practiſe from liſting themſelves in the number of ſome numerous party, colloguing with Midwives and Nurſes, as I believe them for the generality very falſe, ſo admit them true, yet have they much more honeſty then that uſed by theſe new pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to advance themſelves by defaming all others, nay thoſe great Maſters, to whoſe labours all the world is beholding, that by this means they may work upon the credulity of ignorant perſons, unable to judge in any Science, much leſs in that of Phyſick.</p>
            <p>After this, and an excurſion in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of himſelf and Mr. <hi>Bolneſt,</hi> with a ſlight neglect put upon others, he falls upon Dr. <hi>Sprackling,</hi> the Author of <hi>Medela Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiae,</hi> whom he ſcorns to name, leſt the world ſhould take notice of him by this great perſons vouchſafing any thing in reply to what he ſaith, but tells you, he calls him illiterate, (which, by the way, is not applied to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:55561:11"/>but his plea) but if he had done ſo, Mr. <hi>Nedham</hi> is not behind-hand, for within a few lines he reckons him among <hi>the ſlight Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that are made Doctors, talks of other ſmall Beagles and little Doctoral fellows at the Preſs ready to open againſt him, but that neither he nor the Book-buyers ſhall take notice of them, in a conteſt which it rather concerns their grave and formal Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to clear if they can, and the world</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>hath reaſon to expect it from them.</hi> And upon the ſame ſubject quotes a ſentence out of <hi>Joſeph Scaliger,</hi> who being told that an obſcure fellow had written mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertly againſt him, expreſſeth himſelf thus, <hi>Mihi relatum fuit Scarabeum quendam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra me ſcribere cui reſpondere neque digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis eſt nec otii.</hi> I confeſs I diſlike not Mr. <hi>Nedham</hi>'s artifice to neglect a reply, to what it may be is not ſo eaſily anſwered, and that under pretence of giving the obſcure Writers ſome name and reputation, by this Champions appearing in the liſts againſt them. Did he not at the ſame time endeavour to raiſe to himſelf ſome glory and renown by provoking more learned Pens to write againſt him? But I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb facs="tcp:55561:11"/>he will fail in this particular, and go away with the reward of the poor Vicar, who in the times of Rebellion got to preach at <hi>White-hal</hi> before <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> and there inveighed bitterly both againſt him and all the proceedings of thoſe times; inſomuch that <hi>Oliver</hi> had it in debate to queſtion him for his Sermon, till a wiſer man repreſented unto him, that he was an obſcure perſon, who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by this means onely to get himſelf a name and better living from that party which was loyal to His Majeſty, after, it may be, a month or two of impriſonment; whereas other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if he were let alone, the Sermon would die and the man be forgotten: which counſel was followed with a ſucceſs according to that prognoſtick. But leſt our Authar ſhould glory too much in the example of <hi>Joſeph Scaliger,</hi> and think himſelf equal to that great man in learning, and therefore imitate him in his pride in reviling and ſcorning others, as Mr. <hi>Nedham</hi> doth: give me leave to tell the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the whole ſtory of that paſſage, and the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of it, which, if this Gentleman's intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence had not failed him, he might have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to himſelf and eaſed me. Thus it was:
<pb facs="tcp:55561:12"/>One <hi>Thomas Lidiat,</hi> Vicar of a poor Town called <hi>Alkerton</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> or the edge of it, a very learned man, but eſpecially in Chronological learning, happened to put out a Book <hi>de emendatione temporum,</hi> much about the ſame time, yet before that large one of <hi>Scaligers,</hi> of the ſame Title, in which <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat</hi> falling upon many Notions that <hi>Scali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> had, and differing from him in others, particularly in the time of the Birth of our Saviour, which <hi>Lidiat</hi> puts four years before <hi>Scaliger;</hi> this incited the learned man, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> could not well brook a contradiction, to writ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an Anſwer to <hi>Lidiat</hi>'s Book, in which he ſlights the poor man, calls him in ſcorn <hi>Anglus homo &amp; neſcio quis propheta,</hi> with ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> like ſcoffs. But ſoon after <hi>Lidiat</hi> replies againſt this Anſwer, and juſtifies himſelf both ſolidly and modeſtly; but whilſt this Boo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was in hand, <hi>Scaliger</hi> thought fit to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an Anſwer, before it came out, in the word quoted by Mr. <hi>Nedham.</hi> Other it never had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Many thought then and do ſtill, becauſe hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reaſons were too ſtrong to be refuted. But n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> long after the poor man lying in his bed ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his houſe broken, and was himſelf ſore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:55561:12"/>beaten and wounded by diſguiſed perſons, who were never known, nor took thence the value of one farthing: inſomuch that many ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that uſage to come from the forge of <hi>Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liger,</hi> who not being able to anſwer his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, thought fit to be revenged upon him with clubs. The relation of this laſt paſſage I had from the mouth of a perſon of great integrity, who ſaw and ſpake with him when his face was ſwelled, and ill with the ſaid beating. Let Mr. <hi>Nedham</hi> take heed that the firſt part of this Relation be not applicable to him; and if he ſhall hereafter think fit to engage himſelf farther againſt <hi>Hippocrates, Galen,</hi> and all the Ancients, I ſhould adviſe him to write in ſome language that may carry his conceits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our <hi>Engliſh</hi> world, that other Nations may both judge of the controverſie, and either ſubmit to his determination, or vindicate thoſe Authors, if none in <hi>England</hi> ſhall think fit to do it. The reſt of his Epiſtle is but a ſhort abridgment of what lies ſcattered in his Book, and is there ſpoken to. There onely reſts now that I ſhould advertiſe the Reader, that this Treatiſe, ſuch as it is, had come out ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny months ſooner, had not the Viſitation by
<pb facs="tcp:55561:13"/>the hand of God hindred the going on of the Preſs. My abſence upon other occaſions, and the Corrector's careleſneſs have cauſed ſome faults to have eſcaped the Preſs, chiefly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral, in the omiſsion of a letter ſometimes in the <hi>Greek</hi> quotations, other times mis-accen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſometimes falſe ſpelling; all which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Reader will, I hope, candidly correct, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to blot out the word <hi>ſmattering</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> third page, which I aſſure him was not in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Copy ſent by me to the Preſs, however it crep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in, as did alſo the Titular Superſcriptions i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome of the leavs of the firſt and ſecond ſheets which I deſire Mr. <hi>Nedham</hi> as well as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Reader to believe were not my own, who nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affect lightneſs nor abuſe toward one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> know not to have ever ſeen or ſpoken with.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55561:13"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Medicina Veterum Vindicata:</hi> OR, A JUSTIFICATION Of the <hi>Ancient Method</hi> OF PHYSICK.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this ſcribling Age wherin we live, and in which all men take li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to preſent the world with things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, or pretended to be ſo, to precedent Ages, I have not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved any Profeſsions more aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by theſe bold attempters, than the three moſt noble, Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Law, and Phyſick. The firſt directing us to a future happineſs,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55561:14"/>as we are men endued with Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and an Immortal Soul. The ſecond, as we are a Society of men to be kept and governed by ſuch rules and directions, as are fit to preſerve the whole in Unity and Peace with one another. The third, as we are natural bodies, made up of ſuch a harmony and conjunction of parts, which being fitly united together and ſo kept, each of them ſubſervient to the other in their proper Functions, preſerve the whole intire as a fit Inſtrument for the Soul to exerciſe her faculties by.</p>
            <p>I ſhall let paſs the two firſt, as not proper to my Profeſsion or undertaking, but leave it to the ſad conſideration of thoſe that are expert in thoſe Profeſsions, if the very foundations, and moſt received Maxims of them both have not been ſtruck at by ſome late pretenders to a greater mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of knowledge, or revelation,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55561:14"/>than their Brethren. In Phyſick, what almoſt has not been attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by confident and over-bold perſons, who though they would be thought Maſters of much more knowledge than their neighbors, will yet upon examination be found not to have peirced ſo deep as others have, into the right knowledge and underſtanding of the firſt <hi>praecognita,</hi> without which, it is impoſsible to lay any ſolid foundation, upon which either themſelves or others may ſafely raiſe any permanent ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructure? Amongſt many, I find none ſeems more aſſured of his cauſe, than an Anonymous Writer, yet well enough known under his veil, and is it ſeems, a perſon of ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> underſtanding in Phyſick and other parts of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet who from ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynted paſſages in ſeveral both Antient and Modern Writers, and ſome uncontroverted truths,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55561:15"/>would make us believe that the Art of Phyſick lay ſick, and almoſt deſperate, except ſupported by his helping hand; but indeed, in ſtead of a Cordial, preſents us a Purgative potion, which if taken, would ſoon ſend her to the grave, and leave nothing to ariſe from her ruines but ignorance and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. I muſt however give him thanks for his pains and labor, <hi>Saepe etiam olitor eſt opportuna locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus:</hi> but truely ſhall adviſe none to buy his Medicine, who from ſome ſcattered Collections out of good authors, endeavors to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the memories of thoſe noble Artificers, and to ſhake the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation which with ſo much wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath been laid by them, and ſince happily built upon by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Perhaps I ſhall find it a leſs eaſie task to anſwer him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, than ſome man at the firſt reading his Book may imagine, and that chiefly for two Reaſons.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:55561:15"/>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe it will be always found a more eaſie task to diſpute with any Adverſary, than with him, whoſe confidence makes him adventure at the denial of thoſe very Principles upon which the Art is built, and that have paſſed the approbation of the learnedſt of many Ages, and that upon full conſideration, and, as moſt of the world hath ſince judged, a full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of what then was, or ſince is (for I find little materially new) urged againſt them; I mean the compoſition of bodies from the four. Elements, the doctrine of the Humors, and the combination of Qualities, of which I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeak hereafter: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch a man cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, without telling over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain thoſe Reaſons that indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Antients, both to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them rational, and lay them down as things fit to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved; and are like thoſe Eccen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55561:16"/>Circles and Epicycles in Aſtronomy, which are not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily true, yet ſerve to reconcile appearances, and therefore are of equal value, as if they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly ſo; ſince by them we are brought to a certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of that truth we ſeek for, at leaſt ſuch a knowledge as the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing ſought for is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe I find this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor make uſe of many laudable ſayings, both of Ancient and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Writers, inverting them to clean different ſenſes than what they were produced for, as I ſhall in their examination, I hope, make very manifeſt. Inſomuch that I have very much doubted, whether this Writer be not ſomewhat of kind with thoſe perſons whom <hi>Ariſtole</hi> ſpeaks of in his 30. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem, Sect.</hi> 1. who being otherwiſe ſober and grave, yet through ſome paſsion that tranſports them, are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55561:16"/>taken with ſuch fits and fancies, that tis hard to diſtinguiſh whether they owe this to any acquired in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition, or rather to a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral temperature of the body: his words are theſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And truely had not this irregular work of his been in ſome meaſure of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral concern, I ſhould unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have been drawn to have awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him out of ſo pleaſing a rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but have allowed him that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn which the Emperor (if I miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take not, <hi>Commodus</hi>) is reported to have thought him worthy of, who in the paſtime of darting at a Bull, uſed by the <hi>Romans,</hi> had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately miſſed his mark many times, the Emperor cauſed money to be given him, with theſe words, <hi>That twas praiſe-worthy to be excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently ill.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:55561:17"/>
            <p>But let me now come to a little neerer conſideration of the book it ſelf, and in it begin with his firſt Chapter, whoſe title is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is for the good of mankind there ſhould be a liberty allowed in the profeſſion of Phyſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What he means by this equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal word, <hi>Liberty in the Profeſſion of Phyſick,</hi> I well underſtand not; tis capable I think but of three in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, that it ſhould be free for all men to make that their Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Profeſsion, and uſe all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable endeavors to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves capable of that faculty.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, a liberty in the examining and judging the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of thoſe went before us, and adhere to them ſo farr as they do to Reaſon. A liberty in theſe two ſenſes, was (that I know of) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver denyed to any, nor a greater than this ever conteſted for by any Learned man. This, and no more
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55561:17"/>will his quotations out of <hi>Galen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 3.</note> out of <hi>Langius,</hi> my Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> and all the reſt warrant, who in all their quotations, and the deſign of all whoſe writing was no more than to encourage all men in the enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry after truth, and new diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries thereof, in which he is ſo far from having me his adverſay, that I ſhall embrace him and his deſign, and approve of them to my utmoſt power, ſo that with modeſty he propound his notions, and not magiſterially deliver them, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates capable from his ſingle au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and leſs experience, to overthrow all that hath been laid down before him. But that the overthrow of all before him, is part of his meaning, I am the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther induced to believe, from his raſh cenſure upon thoſe who did not at the firſt propoſition embrace the new doctrine of <hi>Ticho, Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont, Harvey, Quercetane,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as you may ſee from the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55561:18"/>twelfth Page, to the end of the firſt Chapter.</p>
            <p>Is not this againſt his own rule quoted out of my Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> p. 6. <hi>Antiquity deſerves that men ſhould make a ſtay a while, and ſtand thereupon,</hi> &amp;c? and doth not he live to ſee every one of theſe men poſſeſſed of their due honor, and their truths, ſuch of them as are found to be ſo, embraced with gladneſs? Who is more famous or eſteemed all the world over, than the moſt learned Dr. <hi>Harvey,</hi> whoſe ſtatue ſet up in the publike Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, and Anniverſary Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon his account will preſerve his memory perhaps longer than the numerous more noble progeny deduced from other branches of that ancient and deſerving family, whoſe notions have been more improved, and whoſe writings in their kind more admired? Why doth he ſo much blame the cenſure of the Phyſicians at <hi>Paris,</hi> upon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55561:18"/>the Spagyrical works of <hi>Querce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane,</hi> when as in truth there was no more than a prohibition of the uſe of them, till after a convenient ſtand made upon them, they had paſt their tryal, and with their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, both received, the one as good Medicines, the other as a learned man? We muſt allow ſomething to the heat and paſsion of men, who being exaſperated, have not always that temper and moderation required; the like may be ſaid to their cenſure upon Sir <hi>Theodore de Mayern,</hi> whoſe rough language is more condemned than any thing elſe; and it ſoon appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the world, what eſtimation they both deſervedly had, and were both as great admirers and followers of the rational way in the practice of Phyſick, as any that went before them. Certainly this Writer, if he have any ingenuity, cannot but acknowledge, that tis not reaſonable to make uſe of any
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55561:19"/>new remedy, either Spagyrical or other, whoſe virtues are not at all known ſo much as <hi>in baſi,</hi> untill by ſome convenient experience it had been approved to be effectual to that end for which it is produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
            <p>As for the purpoſe, put caſe ſome new Plant, Root, or Mineral ſhould be brought from any Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein part of the world, or found at home, of which there were no foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps to be found in the <hi>materiae medica,</hi> would not he be a bold adventurer that ſhould make uſe of this in Phyſick, till he were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured it were not endued with a Noxious, rather than a Medicinal quality? Nay, admit he were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, would he condemn all others that came not immediately to the like aſſurance, till they might have time to ground it upon ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent experience? This was the caſe with <hi>Quercetane</hi> and other Chymiſts at the firſt; the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55561:19"/>of which Art (though in it ſelf good and profitable) we muſt attribute to that <hi>Auri ſacra fames.</hi> For men having in vain laboured from the Aenigmatical writings of thoſe Philoſophers, which are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Adepti,</hi> to find out that Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Medicine, which ſhould not onely cure all diſeaſes, but likewiſe their itch of Gold, by turning all metalls into it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Philoſophers ſtone, were loth, when they ſaw themſelves deceived, to loſe all their labor, but not being able to cure themſelves in whole, thought fit to propound what they had found, as fit Medicines for the cure of diſeaſes, that by this means they might give a palliative cure to their own covetouſneſs, and in ſome meaſure re-impurſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of ſome part of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, they had been, by cunning knaves, either cheated of, or them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves vainly expended. Since
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55561:20"/>which time this Art hath, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, been much cultivated by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Learned men, and to a much better end. I mean to the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Phyſick, whoſe labours therein deſerve their due praiſe, ſo as they do not make uſe of the Daughter to pluck out the eyes of her Mother; and under pretence of Medicines, that forſooth muſt operate by occult qualities, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible tranſpirations, thruſt out of doors all thoſe that operate by thoſe that are known and diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and indeed reduce all the <hi>materia medica,</hi> to the narrow compaſs of the <hi>Minerologia;</hi> for moſt of their preparations are out of a few of them, to wit, <hi>Vitriol, Antimony, Salt-peter, Sulphur, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> and perhaps one or two more; to the end that with the help of three or four bottles car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in their pocket, they might ſupply the office of all other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies uſed by the Dogmaticks, as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55561:20"/>they in reproach ſtyle them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in truth I dare confidently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow, that ſome of them have as much practiſed, and better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the way of Chymical prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, than the ableſt of theſe pretenders do; they differ onely in this, the one makes uſe of them when his reaſon and judgement di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect him they may be uſeful; the other promiſcuouſly and at adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; whoſe argumentations for the moſt part run thus (eſpecially if at any time they deal in Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables) ſuch and ſuch a Vegetable is good in ſuch a caſe, being taken into the body, therefore it ſhall be much more effectual if it be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the Spirit, Salt, Extract, or the like; whereas in truth they are deceived, and many or moſt of them operate beſt, being given in ſubſtance, and the body left to make its own extraction. I ſhall let paſs his immenſe commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> and <hi>Van Helmont,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55561:21"/>whoſe writings are to my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo obſcure, that I ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear any cenſure upon them, till this or ſome other charitable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall make me clearly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the meaning of them.</p>
            <p>I come now to the third and laſt way of the acceptation of theſe words, <hi>Liberty in the Profeſſion of Phyſick.</hi> That is, a liberty for all men to profeſs and practiſe it, that will pretend themſelves knowing in it, whether Students in the Art or not; if ſo, then why not in all other profeſsions whatſoever, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, Law, Muſick, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> a liberty which ſome of thoſe perſons, who call themſelves <hi>Gifted Brethren,</hi> have endeavoured to bring in: Scorners of all humane Learning, many of which have appeared up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Stage of late, and whoſe dictates muſt of neceſsity be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted upon <hi>liberty</hi> taken in this ſenſe. Nay then, why not a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in profeſsing all Trades? which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55561:21"/>muſt bring a diſorder and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the whole.</p>
            <p>For a liberty of practice in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of the remedies, the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their Medicines, the judging the diſeaſe, was never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed to any Phyſician. But he that ſhall more narrowly look into this Writers deſign, will eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his intention to be to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce an Empirical way of practice, wherein the practiſers under-bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed names, ſuch as <hi>Kibrick, Azoth, Alkaheſt, Drif,</hi> and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſuch uſed frequently by ſome of that crew, would make the world believe themſelves Maſters of great ſecrets, which by inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ways of operations muſt cure all diſeaſes, and by that means open a door to ignorance and pride; for truely what needs any man Study Phyſiology or Patho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, when at the firſt turn he comes to the laſt round of the lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Therapeuticks?</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:55561:22"/>
            <p>Tis true indeed, they pretend a great deal of Charity to the poor, but the very plain truth is, tis to themſelves, that, by diſgracing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they may bring cuſtome to their Shops.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not be obliged to uſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny arguments to prove that this is his main end. He that ſhall throughly read his Book, will ſee that poyſon ſcattered through all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every leaf of it. I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſome of thoſe paſſages, to which peradventure I ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſpeak more largely. <hi>Pag.</hi> 92. He tells you much miſchief is often done by the uſe of ſuch Medicines as in the common opinion have a paſport every where to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed againſt the Scurvy, as Scurvy-graſs, Water-creſſes, and the like; what is this but upon his ſingle authority, and a freak of his own brain, to ſhake the uſe of all Specificks in others, and yet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf propound no better? and if
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55561:22"/>not he (I am ſure moſt of that crew) pretend by ſome one ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick Medicine, which forſooth muſt be held as a great ſecret, to cure all diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 149. and forward to 153. He falls upon a large commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Helmont,</hi> in theſe words, The moſt acute and noble <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> (whoſe doctrine, ſo much of it as he had laboured to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, he could not but admire) and then from his Authority, and the example of one child ſo brought up by him, would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the world againſt bringing up children from the Breaſt, and have them all ſuckled by hand; and this from a conceit, that all the world is infected with the Pox, Scurvy, and I know not what complication of diſeaſes; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in truth, admitting this were true, twill ſecure you onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Nurſe (in the choice of whom commonly great care is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken)
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55561:23"/>and not againſt the Parents, from whom is the greateſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>Beſide, tis obſervable, that he makes almoſt, if not all diſeaſes, not onely infectious by taction, but to tranſmit their poiſon at a diſtance by communication, breathing, and the like; ſo that upon this account he muſt bring the world to a ſolitary and ſingle converſation, or the matter will not be helped.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 211. He diſlikes the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Rational and Empirical, and then tells you the great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit he hath reaped from the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections made from them and old Women. I ſhall tranſcribe his words, though they are long. <hi>But leſt you ſhould think, that I like this Diſtinction in the common uſe of it, let me tell you, that I, who for many years have converſed with ſuch Profeſſors of Phyſick, as ſome in ſcorn term</hi> Empiricks, <hi>and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55561:23"/>their various ways, and thought it no ſhame to make Collections from them, and from all the Old Women I could meet with, which pretended to any thing of Phyſick, could ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom find any of them ſo irrational, as not to give ſome tolerable reaſon, and ſo much as ſatisfied me, that for the moſt part they had reaſon for what they did; and though perhaps their Diſcourſe came not from them, cloathed with ſuch delicate Terms of Art, as paſs current among the Schools, yet giving them ſome grains of Allowance, I concluded they ſpake reaſon, and that their Method was right, becauſe it was ſitted to the Medicines they uſed, and both Method and Medicines ſo well agreed as to make Cures in many deſperate Caſes, left as incurable by others: And I muſt profeſs, that by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Practices of theſe, I have had opportunities to ſee more of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in her naked appearances and operations (as to the condition
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55561:24"/>wherein ſhe now ſtands in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Age) than ever I could diſcover in all the Volumes that I have read. Therefore call men Empiricks, or what you will, becauſe they are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graduated nor incorporated, I ſhall ever eſteem ſuch to be moſt Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, as make Art to follow Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, rather than ſtrain Nature and her Anomalies to general Rules of Art, and who ſeeing Nature degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into Extravagancies never known heretofore, do endeavor to find out new ways and Remedies to deal with her: which he that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heres to that old Philoſophy, which is uſually made the entrance into Phyſick, will never be able to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs this Writer hath had good luck to receive ſuch light from the reaſoning and receipts of ſage women. I have for the beſt part of twenty years been perhaps as curious as another in the peruſing and examining what I have met
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55561:24"/>with in that kind from any of them, but could yet either never or very ſeldom diſcover any good thing in any of them, but general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found, they were the preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſome Phyſician, which he appointed for ſome particular oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion and Patient, and after being tranſcribed into their receit books, have become of univerſal appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all bodys, all conſtitutions, and all tempers, which by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors thereof were not intended to have their operations to ſo large an extent; and hardly one of their Chymical preparations (but ordinary drinks or decocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) for which he onely contends, &amp; for their ſake would overthrow all other Phyſick, both in its foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and method. But in this place, leſt he ſhould ſeem to ſpeak without book, he draws in <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> to be of his party. In his ΠΑΡΑΓΓΕΛΙΑΙ, at the beginning of his book, where he gives directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55561:25"/>to Phyſicians, how to demean themſelves, he commends ratiocina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is joyned with exercitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. then tells you that Ratiocination is a kind of memory, that compounds and puts together what are obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Senſes. He then ſoon after hath theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Which words I muſt thus render: <hi>Simul etiam approbo ratiocinationem, licèt ex fortuito caſu originem ſumpſerit, &amp; impetum vel morbum dirigit me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodicè ex apparentibus;</hi> his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is this, that he approves of their ratiocination, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it had its beginning for ſome accidental chance, provided their reaſon be directed according to the appearances of the diſeaſe. <hi>Mercurialis</hi> renders the words thus, <hi>Collaudo quidem igitur etiam ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinationem
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55561:25"/>ſi ab experientia prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium facit, &amp; comprehenſionem ex apparentibus dirigit.</hi> The dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is not great, if by <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia</hi> he meaneth <hi>caſus fortuitus,</hi> to wit, a Medicine found out by chance, for ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies, and was taken up by Empiricks for any Medicine they fell upon by chance or accident, ſo that <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perientia</hi> is by <hi>Mercurialis</hi> no more but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a trial, and by <hi>compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſio,</hi> he underſtands that <hi>lapſus</hi> or <hi>impetus,</hi> by which the man is overtaken, for ſo the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies, or a diſeaſe. Then after the interpoſition of ſome lines, he tells you, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: That is, that a garrulous aſſeveration is unſafe and ſubject to error; he ſubjoyns thoſe words quoted by our Author, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That a Phyſician ſhould not be backward to hear
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55561:26"/>the diſcourſes of ignorant perſons, if they knew any thing profitable for the cure of the diſeaſe. So that tis clear, that <hi>Hippocrates</hi> here joyns Empirical Medicines with Rational diſcourſes, tells you that reaſon is to compound and aſſume one thing after another, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divided garrulous aſſeverati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are unſafe and erroneous, whereas our Author diſlikes the diſtinction between Rational and Empirical, and undoubtedly would reduce all Phyſick to the laſt, to wit, of hazardous trials grounded upon every mans fancy and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, and the application of all Medicines to all at random.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Hippocrates</hi> adviſes all Phyſicians in this, will willingly be allowed: Why do we other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe read books ſtuffed with Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines and Receipts, but that we might ground our ſelves upon the experience of others, and then
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55561:26"/>uſe our own reaſon and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 14. He tells us that <hi>Regius</hi> has reduced all Phyſick unto the knowledge and curation of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes; whereas tis evident that <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> under the knowledge of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes comprehends all Phyſiology; and though he diſapprove the common doctrine of the manner of the compoſition of bodies by the four Elements, yet he lays down another kind of Philoſophy, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Method of <hi>Deſcartes;</hi> and whoſoever ſhall read him will find the knowledge of his Phyſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy will be as neceſſary to the right judging diſeaſes, as that of the Ancients is by others now eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and though peradventure the knowledge what the diſeaſe is with which a Patient may be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, may many times be obvious to the Standers by, as where an intenſe heat, a high-water, and a quick pulſe meet, tis ordinarily
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55561:27"/>judged that a Fever is there (for which part of knowledge they are yet beholding to the preceding di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of Phyſicians, and the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten return of like ſickneſſes) yet what kind of Fever it is, whether <hi>boni</hi> or <hi>mali moris,</hi> whether <hi>Idiopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thical,</hi> or <hi>Symptomatical,</hi> upon what accident it did invade the body, requires many times the uſe of our beſt reaſon, and not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently upon the knowledge of it run upon the general cure of a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, as this man aims at by his ſo much commending Ignorance and Empiricks.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 17. He tells you <hi>Fernelius</hi> ſpeaks but lightly of Anatomy; and in another place <hi>Galen</hi> of Herbs. Tis true <hi>Plantius</hi> tells you in the life of <hi>Fernelius,</hi> that he diſliked thoſe that did <hi>ad extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum uſque ſenium deſudare in evol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendis anatomicis libris &amp; in cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcendis ſimplicibus medicamentis, nullum interim aegrum inſpicientes
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55561:27"/>nec quae à veteribus prodita ſunt in aegris obſervantes.</hi> He diſlikes the ſpending a mans whole time in reading Anatomy, of which he ſaith there are as many and as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepant, as there are diſeaſes; and ſpending your whole time in that employment without viſiting the ſick, and taking notice of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations of the Ancients; but adviſes you to read diligently ſome one of the beſt, both in Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy and <hi>re herbaria,</hi> ſince a mans life is not ſufficient to read all men. What ſlighting is here of Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, of which he himſelf writ a Tractate? Tis true he adviſes men not to loſe the end of Phyſick, the eaſing of ſick perſons, by ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding altogether upon circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and things precedaneous to it. I need not here enlarge my ſelf in the commendation and neceſſary knowledge of Anatomy, every days experience makes it evident that he that goes about the cure of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55561:28"/>diſeaſes, without a competent knowledge therof, goes wildly and abſurdly to work; which way had <hi>Galen</hi> cured a lame foot, by apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Medicines to the back, had he not known that the Nerves that run down from the ſixt <hi>Verte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre</hi> of the <hi>ſpina dorſi,</hi> had there their riſe? How can any Surgeon with ſafty ſo much as let blood, or make an iſſue, that knows not how the Arteries, Tendons, and Muskles lye? And certainly the Art is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly beholding to thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whoſe induſtry and inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gives them time and will to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more curiouſly into theſe things.</p>
            <p>He that ſhall read <hi>Harveys</hi> works, Dr. <hi>Gliſſons</hi> Book <hi>de anat. hepatis,</hi> Dr. <hi>Wharton de glandulis, Pecket de vaſis chiliferis,</hi> and others, will find how much the world is beholding to them for their pains therein, and the Art enriched by their diſcoveries. I muſt needs ſay
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55561:28"/>of Anatomy and Botanicks, what I have often thought of the general Study of the Mathematicks. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the knowledge of Aſtronomy we ſhould in a ſhort time loſe the account of Time, Navigation, the knowledge of the Stars, the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling Eclipſes and many other things of moſt neceſſary uſe would be ſoon loſt with mankind. So without Geometry, the meaſure of all things would be forgotten, Surveying, Architecture, both Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and Military, and many other things, inſomuch, that were their knowledge of as particular an uſe, as it is of general concernment, thoſe profeſſions muſt be the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rich and admired of the world. But the miſery is, that the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome few men in thoſe Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, is able to ſupply the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a whole Nation. Tis juſt ſo in Anatomy and Botanicks; the curious and uſeful ſpeculations of ſome few, are able to give a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55561:29"/>ſtock of knowledge to all others, without wholly taking them off from their more neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry employment in the cure of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</p>
            <p>It ſhall ſuffice to have marked theſe things in <hi>tranſitu,</hi> by which it may appear how unjuſt his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of that diſtinction of Rational and Empirical is, and may ſerve to ſhew the venome that lyes ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through his whole Book, and eaſe me of ſome labor hereafter in the anſwering the reſt of it; and having thus ſhewed you what li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in the profeſsion of Phyſick was taken by the Ancients, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by all others; and how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and noxious to mankind an Empirical and Tentative way is, I might here make an end of the conſideration of his firſt Chapter, did he not call me into the liſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from a new Topick, not yet by me taken notice of, though at the very beginning, <hi>That tis a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55561:29"/>out queſtion, that diſeaſes of this preſent time are of another nature than they were in former times</hi> (and undertakes to prove this) <hi>and if that be once proved, then it cannot be denyed, we muſt proceed by other definitions of their nature, and inda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of their cauſes, and invent other remedies, reaſons, and rules of curation, than have been delivered by the Ancients.</hi> I muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>hoc magnum quid ſonat,</hi> if he make this good, he and I muſt ſhake hands, and be no more adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. Let me examine his words; <hi>Of another nature.</hi> By nature here he cannot underſtand ſome cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantial change or alteration in the ſubject; as for the purpoſe, a Fever in <hi>Peter</hi> may differ from that of <hi>Paul;</hi> for this will not put us to new Definitions, new indagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, new Aphoriſms, new precepts, and in ſum, of a general new Method, and he cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of that trite Maxim, <hi>aliud eſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55561:30"/>curare morbum, aliud curare Petrum &amp; Paulum.</hi> He muſt therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that either thoſe diſeaſes which were known to the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, are wholly loſt in the world, and New ſprung up again in their room, or that thoſe which were known heretofore, are now quite changed to another ſort and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. I aſk therefore, whether Apoplexies, Fevers, Catarrhs, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lepſies, diſeaſes of the Ears, Eyes, Teeth, and all other treated of by <hi>Hippocrates, Galen, Avicenna,</hi> and the reſt, and now frequently invade mankind, ſtand in need of new De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions and new Curations from any alteration of their nature? If he ſay yes, I then ask from what cauſe this change can come? for if the Diſeaſe be in this manner al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in nature, it muſt neceſſarily follow that the Bodies of all Men and Beaſts which are the ſubjects of them are altered in their nature, as it muſt likewiſe follow, that all
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55561:30"/>Meats, Drinks, Fruits, Herbs, and all things that ſerve for the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of mankind are altered likewiſe in their nature: for it is unreaſonable to believe that the ſame natural agent doth not act alike at all times, <hi>caeteris paribus,</hi> and conſequently, that all diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers that ariſe from the inordinate uſe of thoſe things that ſhould nouriſh the body, or from any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſorder in the uſe of the ſix natural things, are the ſame ſtill, not altered in their nature, and ſo not ſtanding in need of new Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay would it not be conſidered whether this new Doctrine doth not introduce a Tranſmutation of Species? for perhaps it will be as eaſie to change the Species of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as his Nature, and ſo a Mans body become that of an Aſs, as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> thought of the Soul. Does he mean that many perſons now adays in reſpect of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55561:31"/>of one diſeaſe with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, require a different way of treating them than formerly they ought to have had in the ſame caſes? If he mean ſo, tis abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe: for where there is the ſame Complication, the ſame me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in the cure which hath been ſucceſsfully uſed heretofore, may undoubtedly be uſed again. But in this I would not be miſtaken, as if we were neceſsitated to tread in the ſteps of our Anceſtors in the uſe of thoſe very Remedies by them preſcribed (which this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor would fain perſwade us, is the opinion of the Dogmaticks) ſince never any diſeaſes (I believe) ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſimple or complicate, did twice ſo correſpond in every cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance to any obſervation, that there was not latitude enough left to the Phyſician to make uſe of his beſt Judgement and Reaſon in the ſelection of his remedies, and attempering them to the diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:55561:31"/>and conſtitution of his Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</p>
            <p>Or laſtly, is it his intention to ſhew, that in this laſt Age of the world, there is a Complication of many new diſeaſes not known to the Ancients, and now generally raging? This ſeems probable to be ſome part of his meaning from the whole ſcope of his three next Chapters, chiefly the fourth, where he endeavors to ſhew, that there is now a complication of the <hi>Lues ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerea, Scorbute, vermination,</hi> &amp;c. and I know not what fermentation and ſeminal productions contracted ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from new diſorders, or brought by contagion from our Parents, which quite alter the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of diſeaſes</p>
            <p>Should all this be granted him, of which there is not one part but is queſtionable; for he cannot but know that many grave Authors are of opinion, that the Scorbute and Pox were both known to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55561:32"/>as well as Vermination; he would from hence obtain no more than that liberty which <hi>Hippocrates</hi> took, and was never denyed, to make uſe of his own judgement, as well in diſcerning as curing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes. Neither have the late diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of the Motion of the heart, Circulation of the bloud, the uſe of the parts ordained for the diſtribution of the Chile over the body, and the Sanguification of it, any whit changed the nature of the diſeaſes formerly known, or altered the method of their cure. As for the purpoſe, put caſe the Ancients miſtook much in the office of the Liver, but found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many other, that <hi>Agrimony</hi> was very effectual in the cure of many diſeaſes, whoſe ſeat they took to be there, called them He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patick Herbs, which perhaps per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed their office by deputing the bloud, which was carryed to the Heart another way, and might
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55561:32"/>therefore more rationally have been called Cardiacal; doth it hence follow, that their virtue is different in the cure of thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes that are ſtill the ſame, though peradventure we have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in their ſeats?</p>
            <p>But after this it may perhaps be ſaid, that thoſe diſeaſes that have by the ancient method been taken away by Evacuation, <hi>viz.</hi> Purging, Bleeding, Sweating, Urine, or the like, may be taken away by ſome other way, different from any of thoſe mentioned before, that is to ſay, by ſome Univerſal Medicine, of ſo great Analogy with the natural Balſame of the body, that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe ſhall be taken away by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible way of operation, which ſhall require none of the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned helps to be uſed. This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was <hi>Helmonts</hi> way, who by his Alkaheſt and Alterative, would cure moſt diſeaſes without Bleeding, and ſeems to be the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55561:33"/>mind of this Author too, who <hi>Pag.</hi> 46. tells you, <hi>he would write a treatiſe of the miſchief done by bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in moſt diſeaſes.</hi> Truly, if ſuch an Univerſal Medicine be in nature, the Art would be extremely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to that man ſhould diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it to the benefit of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <p>But yet let him, who ever he be, conſider, that this is not yet enough to alter the ancient tryed method, practiſed for many Ages, though it be another different from it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there may be, and perhaps are, ſeveral ways of bringing to paſs the ſame effect or end. If a man ſhall tell you by experience, and many years travel, he hath found it a good way from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>York</hi> to go by <hi>Lincoln,</hi> another by <hi>Nottingham,</hi> is the way to <hi>York</hi> altered by the one or the other method of bringing you thither? Juſt ſo tis with this great Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the nature of diſeaſes is alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55561:33"/>new indagations, new cauſes,
<note place="margin">Pag 2. Pag. 237, 238.</note> new cures muſt be found. Phyſick muſt be rebuilt from the very ground, and have a new founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Philoſophical principles falſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In his ſeventh Chapter at large. So that we muſt caſt off whatever our Reaſon and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment has found profitable in the cure of diſeaſes, and preſerving the health of mankind, and all this upon his bare teſtimony and unknown method, not backed with the authority of one Age. A man meets with a Porter heavily burthened, tells him, Friend, I ſee you laden, and faint under your burthen, I have an invention that if you put it upon your back will make your burthen ſeem lighter. Another tells him, Friend, I ſee you laden, I will take part of your burthen from you, and then you will eaſily maſter the reſt; which of the two is likelieſt to gain cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit? The caſe is alike. A ſick
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55561:34"/>man troubled with a Calenture, Pleuriſie, or the like, in which the bloud being inflamed, diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the whole. One tells him, Sir, I have an Alterative Medicine will cure this diſtemper, as I have often tryed by experience, without Bleeding, or any other expence of time or Phyſick; another tells him, Sir, many hundred years experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence evince, that by Bleeding, this diſeaſe of yours may be cured, and the other method is not more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain than this, and not backed with the like experience. Were he not mad ſhould relinquiſh the firſt for the ſecond? I very well remember a learned Phyſician, in a part of <hi>France</hi> where I then was, who upon the reading <hi>Van Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont de Febribus,</hi> reſolved to quit the Ancient, and follow his New way by Alterative Medicines to cure all Fevers he there met with without letting his Patients bloud; but 'twas accordingly obſerv'd, that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55561:34"/>in the ſpace of ſix moneths, more had dyed under his hand, than he had been obſerved to have cured in many years before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Foreſtus</hi> tells you in his obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>de Febre quartana,</hi> of one in <hi>Delf,</hi> as I remember, that having been troubled a whole yeer with a Quartane, and in vain uſed the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the ableſt Phyſicians, was thus cured by an Empirick, He was adviſed to drink about a quart of very ſtrong wine juſt when he expected his fit, and then to annoint his body all over with butter, and roaſt himſelf by a fire, enduring as much heat as he could poſsible. This Medicine cured him, and made him very jocund, and himſelf now become the ableſt Phyſician for that diſeaſe in the world. It fell out, the next fall of the leaf his Ague returned, and he to his Medicine, but inſtead of being cured, was found dead the next morning; the Obſerver hath
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55561:35"/>this note upon it, that the Humor being the firſt time by much uſe of Phyſick, rationally applyed, well prepared, might give way to that violent remedy, which it would not do the ſecond time when twas crude and unprepared. So falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and uncertain are their new ways, where the Ancient Method is rejected for another not more certain and leſs reaſonable. We have lately ſeen how dangerous it is to ſhake foundations without e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting more firm in their room; and I wiſh theſe new Undertakers would before they diſcountenance the old, ſet us up a new body of Phyſick that might as well ſatisfie our judgments as tie our hands. But I have yet never been ſo happy to meet with two of them that agreed in the ſame Method, but every one pretended himſelf to be the moſt skillful and poſſeſſed of the moſt Univerſal Medicine of any other. One pretends to have an
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55561:35"/>Univerſal Powder, another a Salt, another an Oyl, a fourth a Spirit, and he that is poſſeſſed of one of theſe, ſhall generally as much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry all the reſt, as they ſhall all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to deery the Rational Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, when in truth their aim is to cure onely their own Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that by diſgracing others they might ſet up themſelves.</p>
            <p>Immediately after his demand of liberty of profeſsion of Phyſick, from the alteration and change of the nature of Diſeaſes, he falls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> tells you, <hi>he took a liberty by ſtrength of Reaſon to judge and condemn the opinions and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of ſuch as went before him.</hi> That he writ a body of Phyſick I allow, and ſuch a one as hath been approved by the whole world, but that he condemns the opinions and practices of ſuch as went before, this confident Aſſertor ſhould have done well to have ſhewed us, till when this muſt be lookt upon as a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:55561:36"/>Calumny he makes uſe of to fit his turn, for his greater end of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracing the Art of Phyſick, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept one of his own ſetting up; then he goes on and ſaith, <hi>He may be called the Father of the four Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and of the four fancies cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Humors; which our</hi> Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes <hi>(as ſome call him) Doctor</hi> Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey <hi>approves not, and allows but one.</hi> How candidly he dealt with the old <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> we have had occaſion to ſpeak before; let us now ſee if he deal any better with the New one, as he terms him. He, after he had in his 50. Exercitation aſſerted againſt <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that the Blood, and not the Heart, was <hi>Prima particula genitalis, itaque ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Ariſtoteli ipſi aſſentiri poſſum qui Cor eſſe particulam hanc primam ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitalem &amp; animatam ſtatuit;</hi> in his 51. Exercitation he handles it as it is <hi>pars principalis,</hi> ſhews, that before any thing elſe of the body is diſcernable, that the Blood hath
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55561:36"/>both its birth and increaſe, backs this with the authority of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> (of whom, by the way, no man was a greater admirer than Dr. <hi>Harvey,</hi> who hath often to my ſelf ſaid, who had the honor to know him many years, that he was the moſt rational and acute Philoſopher that ever lived, that his writings were neer divine, that he never met with any thing in Philoſophy, of which he met not ſome track in him) <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> I ſay in his book <hi>De hiſtor. anim. cap.</hi> 19. hath theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>That the blood always beats in the veins of living creatures; that tis the only humor that diſperſeth it ſelf all over the body, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways lives as long as the body
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55561:37"/>lives. That it is firſt begot in the heart before the living creature is perfected. After this he falls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that controverſie, whether the office of the Blood be onely for the Aliment of the body, ſaith, <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and all the School affirm it. The words, though long, I muſt tranſcribe. <hi>Nec de alter â con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſiâ (num ſanguis ſc. nutriendo ſolum corpori inſerviat?) hic anxiè diſputandi locus eſt. Ariſtoteles qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem plurimis in locis ſanguinem eſſe ultimum alimentum contendit, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demque tota medicorum ſchola ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragatur. Plurima tamen explicatu ardua maléque cohaerentia hanc illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſententiam conſequuntur. Cum enim Medici in Phyſiologicis ſuis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt de Sanguine, atque hunc ſolum ejus uſum, &amp; finem docent ut ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum corpori ſuppeditet; eum ex quatuor ſuccis ſeu humoribus compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hunt; argumentum ejus rei à qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor humorum combinationibus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducentes, ac proinde aſſerunt maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:55561:37"/>ſanguinis ex utraque bile (flavâ nempe &amp; atrâ) pituitâ &amp; ſanguine propriè dicto componi: Ideoque qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor humorum genera recenſent; quorum frigidus &amp; humidus Pituita dicitur, frigidus &amp; ſiccus Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholia: calidus &amp; ſiccus Bilis, deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que calidus &amp; humidus Sanguis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatur. Porro ex ſingulis eorum generibus alios Nutritios (unde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum corpus conſtet) Excrementitios alios ſtatuunt. Praeterea ex nutritiis illis (ſeu partibus heterogeneis) San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem conſtare autumant, ita ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ut Pituita ſit pars crudior, quam calor nativus validior poſſit in San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem laudabilem convertere. Bilem vero in Sanguinem tranſire poſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, licèt Sanguinem facile in Bilem atque hanc in Melancholiam (nempe à caloris concoquentis exceſſu) mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari, affirment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quae ſi vera ſunt, nulluſque in iis regreſſus conceditur; ſcil. de Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholia in Bilem, de Bile in Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem: oportet fateantur dictos omnes
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55561:38"/>ſuccos eſſe in ordine ad Melancholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, atque hanc eſſe principale, &amp; maximè concoctum nutrimentum. Quin etiam duplicem Sanguinem ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcant neceſſe eſt: nempe totam ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul in venis maſſam, ex quatuor illis humoribus compoſitam, &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ejus puriorem, florentiorem, magiſque ſpiritalem, quam ſtrictiori ſenſu Sanguinem nominant, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que aliqui in arteriis ſeparatim con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineri contendunt. Ideoque ex eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſententia Sanguis purus non eſt alimentum, ſed commixti ſucci, ſive potius Melancholia, ad quam tandem reliqui humores pertendunt.</hi> The queſtion he handles in this is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all concerning the number of the Humors, but whether the Bloud ſerve onely for the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the body, and whether it be the laſt aliment; tells you, that the whole School of Philoſophers and Phyſicians affirm it; tells you, there are ſome things hard to be explained; ſaith, that Phyſicians
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55561:38"/>who make its office be to ſupply nouriſhment to the body, compoſe it of the four Humors, Pituitoſe, Choler Yellow and Black, and Bloud, to wit pure; that thoſe Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors cannot have any return unto Blood, though the Blood may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be changed into Choler, and that into Melancholy; and then aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes, If theſe things be ſo, and that it be true that there be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs from any of the Humors into pure Bloud again (neither of which he poſitively affirms) that theſe things will then follow, that Melancholy is the moſt concocted nutriment; and next, that there are two ſorts of Blood, one moſt pure, the other compoſed of the four Humors; and that pure Blood is not alone the aliment of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but the commixed Humors, or rather Melancholy, to which the other tend. I confeſs I ſee not here <hi>nec volam nec veſtigium</hi> of the denial of the Humors, nor any
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55561:39"/>abſurdity, either in the affirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Schools, or incoherence in his aſſumption from what they ſay. He that ſaith, that Blood con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of the four Humors, doth ſupply the <hi>ultimum alimentum</hi> to the body, doth not ſay any one alone of them ſeparated from the reſt doth ſupply any aliment at all, no more than he that ſhall ſay Bread doth nouriſh, is bound to affirm that any one conſtitutive part of it, or any <hi>res contenta</hi> in it ſeparated from <hi>re compoſita,</hi> doth ſo; for that may be true in <hi>toto compoſito,</hi> which is not true in any one of its parts ſeparated from the reſt; ſo that that part of Dr. <hi>Harveys</hi> aſſumption will be eaſily granted, that Pure Bloud alone is no nutriment to the body, but the whole maſs as it is conjoyned with the Humors, that is, as he calls them, the <hi>commixti ſucci.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:55561:39"/>
            <p>In the next place he doth truly aſſume, that if there be no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of any of the Humors into Blood back again, and that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy be the laſt, it will truly follow, that it is the moſt concoct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but not that it is the beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted, for 'tis over baked, <hi>(nem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe ex caloris conſequentis exceſſu)</hi> ſo not the principal and chiefeſt nutriment, as he ſeems to affirm, though it be the laſt acc. to <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> but doth not follow from the Opinion laid down by the Schools. But pray what is here againſt the Four Humours? Doth he that ſaith Melancholy is the laſt and moſt concocted, and to which the other Humours ſeem to tend; doth he ſay, there is but one, (nay, doth he not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary rather?) Or if they tend to that Humour, do they tend thither to be ſwallowed up by it, or as they may ſtand together <hi>in compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſito?</hi> Yet by the way 'tis to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:55561:40"/>that neither Dr. <hi>Harvey,</hi> or any other, by Compoſition do underſtand the Humours to be <hi>Principia Sanguinis,</hi> for that were to confound them with the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; whereas they knew, or at leaſt thought they did ſo, that every one of thoſe Humours were compounded of the four Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and were Mixt bodies: but by Compoſition they underſtood onely they were there, or things contained in the whole. So that for ought I ſee, the later <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> doth not at all fight againſt the firſt, but leaves him to juſtifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon his own Reaſons largely deduced in his Book, ΠΕΡΙ ΦΥΣΙΟΣ ΑΝΘΡΩΠΟΥ, which Book I wiſh this Author had well read before he had taken upon himſelf the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to call the Four Humours Fancies, or any book of <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> Vain, as he doth that learned book of his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, pag. 243. and in another commends that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55561:40"/>ſaying of <hi>Helmont,</hi> who calls <hi>Galen</hi> the great Corrupter of ſo much as was tolerable in <hi>Hippocrates;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 240.</note> words too big for the mouth of ſuch a Muſhrom as he is in reſpect of <hi>Galen</hi> in all parts of Learning: but I ſhall onely ſay this of him, that 'tis much eaſier to revile a man that is dead, than to have met him in the Schools living.</p>
            <p>I might here very well take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to examine the ancient Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine both of the Compoſition of bodies out of the four Elements, as that of the Humour and Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the four Qualities, but that I ſhall have a ſitter opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for that purpoſe, when I come to examine his Seventh Chapter.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:55561:41"/>
               <head>The Examination of his Second, Third, and Fourth Chapters.</head>
               <p>I Shall conſider theſe Chapters together, becauſe their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are not much different, being onely ſubſervient to prove the neceſſary alteration of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the old Phyſick, and the pulling up the Foundations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, from the alteration of Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes now from what they were anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, and that in reſpect of Worms, (that of Worms I ſhall conſider in the firſt Chapter) Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Womens diſeaſes, the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, Pox, and ſome other. In which I would have it obſerved, that if he had done all this he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, yet the Shooe would be too ſhort for his foot, ſince theſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes would ſtill remain the ſame in their nature, and the alterations require onely a difference of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55561:41"/>in their Compoſition, not either in their ſubſtance or nature, and ſo would not put us to new Precepts and new Foundations, but onely to raiſe ſome Superſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture upon the old. But I believe we ſhall find him fail in all his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts.</p>
               <p>His firſt inſtance is in Agues. Theſe, he tells you, <hi>give the baffle to Phyſicians, being diſtempers quite of another nature, inſomuch that the old Rules and Remedies for the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them are quite out of doors, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom doing good, but generally hurt: as for inſtance, Bloud-letting, which ſhould we in theſe days adminiſter in all Putrid Fevers, (as</hi> Galen <hi>directs, and too many follow) we ſhould make mad work with our Patients, &amp;c. And then hath a fling at</hi> Avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenna, <hi>who gives the ſame precept if the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine be thick and red.</hi> Againſt all theſe Directions of the Ancients he onely oppoſes a new ſort of Quartan in the year 1662, which
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:55561:42"/>had tokens of Malignity, and ſome others in the years 1657 and 1658. both in the Spring and Fall of the year, and in the Autumnal quarter of the other; in which are theſe words,
<note place="margin">Pag. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>Whereas I have obſerved ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally in former years, (and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in this Spring) that bodies either ill-habited or ſcorbutically in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, being phlebotomiz'd for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, have grown very much worſe upon it, &amp;c.</hi> — Then follows a mis-tranſlation of <hi>Sennertus</hi> his words, <hi>Plurimae febres quae hîc aegros infeſtant, omnes notas febrium à Graecis &amp; Arabibus deſcriptas non obtinent:</hi> by him thus rendered; <hi>Moſt Agues which inſeſt men in this age, do not agree with the deſcription of Agues made by the Greeks and Arabians.</hi> Very good. For the firſt part of it, <hi>viz.</hi> that Agues are altered, we have his word and obſervations in the years before mentioned, that the ancient Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies generally hurt, particularly
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:55561:42"/>Bloud-letting, as he generally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in former years, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in this Spring. To this I need make no other Reply, than that other Practiſers, as much in credit, and far more judicious, have not made the like obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; that if he hath found Bloud-letting ſo dangerous in his Patients, he ought rather to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt his own prepoſterous appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of that remedy, without preparation of the Peccant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour before hand, if the Fever were free from Malignity; if Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lign, perhaps his uſing that reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy after the Malignant humour was too much diſſuſed, by which the veins being emptied, drew poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon inſtead of good bloud from the greater veſſels, and ſo transfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Malignity all over the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy more than it was before; with many other cautions fit to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. In the Precepts of the Ancients two things are to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:55561:43"/>notice of; Firſt, that they are given as Directions to Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, not Mountebanks; that the firſt ſhall ſeldom miſs, the laſt as rarely hit, in the purſute of them. Secondly, that as to the matter of Bleeding, we are to conſider that they framed their directions accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the conſtitution of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants in thoſe Countries, where generally drinking Wine, their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies were more eaſily inflamed. I wiſh this <hi>London</hi>-Phyſician would travel over <hi>Spain, Italy, France,</hi> and other hot Countries, and ſee how many Proſelytes he ſhall gain unto this new Doctrine: if I be not deceived, he will find himſelf laughed to ſcorn. Nay, in our own colder Country, I am very confident that remedy of Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in perſons Scorbutically incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hath been many times ſucces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully made uſe of. I love not to brag of my own Knowledge or Practice in Phyſick, I know they
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:55561:43"/>are both very inconſiderable in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of many others; yet this I muſt avow, that I was a Practiſer in thoſe very years by him mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, have had to do with ſome Agu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh and Scorbutical perſons, and in ſome have let bloud, in others for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, as my Judgment led me, but never had that misfortune to turn a Tertian into a Quotidian or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Quartan. But leſt he ſhould be fully without ſhew of Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he rather chuſeth to mis-allege <hi>Sennertus,</hi> whom he makes to ſay that moſt of the Agues now adays agree not with thoſe deſcribed by the Greeks and Arabians; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he ſaith onely, that Agues now a days have <hi>not all thoſe marks</hi> that are recounted by the Greeks and Arabians: there is a great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between <hi>not having at all,</hi> and <hi>not having all.</hi> Does he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that their Deſcriptions were made upon the diſeaſe of one or many men? or did he ever know
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:55561:44"/>that all the marks of any one Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe were at any one time found in the ſame man? Let him take for patern the Scorbute, and tell me whether he ever found all the ſigns deſcribed by <hi>Engalenus, Reuſnerus, Sennertus, Johnſtonus, Riverius,</hi> and others, in any one man. Doth he not know that ſome Agues are exquiſite, ſome baſtard, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time complicated, and ſo all the Marks never or rarely to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to meet in any man? 'Tis enough that the <hi>ſigna idiopathica</hi> are found. When found he in an Intermittent Ague, where there was not a preternatural Heat, an inordinate Pulſe, or Horrour, or ſome one of theſe, if perhaps the Urine might deceive him?</p>
               <p>His next ſtep is to ſhew there is a great alteration as to the ſevere Symptoms now happening to Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in their ſeveral Diſeaſes; but this he paſſeth over without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any reaſon, ſo ſhall I by the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:55561:44"/>bare denial of it; not but that 'tis very eaſie to ſhew that moſt of what happens now to any of that Sex, hath formerly been upon them with as great ſeverity.</p>
               <p>The French Pox comes in the next place, much altered, he tells, from what 'twas at firſt; but as it appears by all his Quotations out of <hi>Fracaſtorius, Fernelius,</hi> and <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nertus,</hi> leſs malignant than at the beginning, and now frequently ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by Contagion without any act of Coition: then he inſtances in the Scorbute and Rickets. Admit all theſe had thoſe variations and alterations he contends for, what is this to the overthrow of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and the Precepts of it? Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe Diſeaſes are new, or old; if new, as ſome hold the two firſt, others doubt, certainly we ſhall onely need Deſcriptions of theſe Diſeaſes, and Methods to cure them, which the Ancients could not give if they knew not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:55561:45"/>the Diſeaſes in ſo particular a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Yet will not the general me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of curing Diſeaſes teach us to judge of the Parts affected, the ſeat of the Diſeaſe, and ſo apply Remedies? How was the Cure at firſt found? by Revelation, or reaſonable Diſcourſe by Learned men among themſelves, and then Experience grounded upon Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Laſtly, if the two firſt of theſe Diſeaſes were unknown, the firſt in <hi>Europe</hi> till the <hi>Spaniard</hi> brought it from the <hi>Indies</hi> to <hi>Naples,</hi> and infected the <hi>French</hi> Army in the year 1590; the later a Diſeaſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to Iſlands, and probably firſt brought in by Seamen, uſed to hard and ſalt meats: doth it thence follow, that no men knew them till we did here?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sen. de lue Ven c. p.</hi> 1.</note> Was the Pox new to the <hi>Indies</hi> who gave it the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> how then had they ſo readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the cure of it? No certainly; 'twas of ſtanding long enough there, and perhaps upon good exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:55561:45"/>will prove to have been in thoſe hot parts but a kind of gentle Leproſie or dry Scab. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much of kind with this is the Scorbute, and but four years dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in their birth, the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſtranger in <hi>Europe</hi> till about the year 1490 and 96,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fern. Sm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>z. p.</hi> 204 <hi>ex sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ngent. Senaer, de Lue Ven. cap</hi> 1.</note> as ſome think; the laſt known firſt in the Northern parts of <hi>Germany</hi> 1486, but not neceſſarily ſo in all the world: then will it fall out that theſe Diſeaſes were not ſo very great ſtrangers to the Ancients.</p>
               <p>'Tis not unknown to any man, that many learned Phyſicians have maintained that the French Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe was known to the Ancients; he that is curious may read what <hi>Valeſius, Reuſnerus</hi> and others have ſaid as to that point, or look what <hi>Sennertus</hi> and <hi>Fallopius</hi> have col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected out of them touching this ſubject; and though they both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline that the Pox doth not anſwer to thoſe Diſeaſes deſcribed by the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:55561:46"/>Ancients, and known in thoſe parts, yet <hi>Sennertus</hi> is very clear, that though it were till about that time beforementioned unknown in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> yet it had been a common gueſt in the <hi>Indies</hi> many ages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and ſo not unknown to the Ancients wholly, nor by them thought of force for its ſake to change the Body of Phyſick.</p>
               <p>Touching the Scorbute, <hi>Senner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> doth with many very ſtrong Arguments prove, that that Diſeaſe was known and deſcribed both by <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not in every thing and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance ſo particularly known as it now is. <hi>Pliny</hi> tells you, that when <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> paſſed the <hi>Rhene,</hi> this Diſeaſe was in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and known by the name of <hi>Stomacace</hi> or <hi>Sceletyrbe:</hi> he adds further,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. hiſt. nat. cap</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Reperta auxilio eſt herba, quae vocatur Britannica, non nervis modo &amp; oris malis ſalutaris, ſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra anginas quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; ſerpentes. Strab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:55561:46"/>tells you, that in the Expedition of <hi>Aelius Gallus</hi> into <hi>Arabia, Hos morbos Arabibus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>populares eſſe refert, Strab. lib.</hi> 16. <hi>in expedit. Aelii Galli.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I might have been very much larger in the deduction of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Authors before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, and many others both of one and the other ſide; but I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be ſhort, and not ſpend time in what (were it never ſo true) would avail very little to overthrow the general Method of curing Diſeaſes, becauſe every day new ones may come up.</p>
               <p>Rickets, Riſing of the Lights, which he takes to be <hi>Hyſterica paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio,</hi> Convulſions, Meaſils, Small Pox, and Scorbutical Gout, come next into play. Touching the firſt, whence it came, where its ſeat is, and a rational way of the cure of it, let the Reader conſult the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:55561:47"/>book of Dr. <hi>Gliſſon</hi> on that ſubject. The reſt, becauſe there was no colour for him to make them ſtrangers to the Ancients, they muſt from the great alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they now have from what for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, require new Precepts and new Methods for their cure. The great ſeverity of theſe Diſeaſes now a days more than heretofore is indeed moſt doubtily proved out of the weekly Bills of Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity collected by Mr. <hi>Grant,</hi> and his own Obſervations, worthy proofs to overthrow an Art by: as if he knew not that in the world there can be no ſo fallacious a way of proof. Every one is enough acquainted with the Searchers, and their way of dealing, who regard nothing more than to give the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral account of the Dead and the Born, and to let the World know when the City is infected with the Plague, with whom nothing is ſo uſual, as to put one Diſeaſe for
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:55561:47"/>another; Conſumptions and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are general names compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending all ſickneſſes whatſoever; and the miſtake is in them no way material, the end being onely to inform the Magiſtrates what Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Sickneſſes reign: and though that way be tolerable in Mr. <hi>Grant,</hi> whoſe deſign is onely to prove the Increaſe and Decreaſe of Mankind; yet from hence to prove the Alteration and Severity of Diſeaſes to the overthrow of all Rules of Phyſick, ſavours too much of Ignorance, Self-ends, or both. He comes after this in his third Chapter to inquire into <hi>the Cauſes of the alterations of diſeaſes from their ancient ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> But till he had proved an Alteration, ſuch as would be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to his purpoſe, in Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, I need not trouble my ſelf to follow him in his Cauſes; yet that I may not ſeem to paſs by any thing he thinks material, I ſhall
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:55561:48"/>trace him in thoſe alſo. 'Tis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable that the ſubject of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Chapter, that there is an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration in Diſeaſes; the third Chapter pretends to ſhew the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this Alteration, to wit, <hi>The Pox and the Scorbute by their inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions made upon the univerſality of Mankind, have been the two main cauſes of this alteration.</hi> What the meaning of theſe plain words is, may perhaps be a little intricate: for if he here underſtand that theſe Diſeaſes are ſolitarily in moſt bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, then certainly their preſence cannot be the cauſe of Alteration of other Diſeaſes that are not there with them. If he underſtand their Complication with other Diſeaſes makes ſuch an Alteration as he contends for, ſo that a Fever, or what elſe, aſſailing the body alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy infected with the Pox or Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, makes ſuch an alteration, as muſt change the Precepts of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick; this is the whole ſubject of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:55561:48"/>his fourth Chapter, and carries ſomething of reaſon in it; but then the third Chapter is wholly uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, or as to thoſe Diſeaſes coinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent with the ſecond, and onely brought in to fill up room, and to bring in one whom he calls Doctor <hi>John Winnels</hi> Preface, and to call this <hi>a wanton, painting, patching,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 69.</note> 
                  <hi>perfuming, iſſuing age.</hi> Certainly all theſe Epithetes have been much more ancient than this age; let him look upon <hi>Jezabel</hi> in the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, <hi>Julia Meſſalina</hi> in the Roman, <hi>Rhodope Criſpa,</hi> of whom <hi>Auſonius</hi> ſpeaks,
<q>
                     <l>Praeter legitimi genitalia foedera coetus,</l>
                     <l>Repperit obſcaenas veneres vitioſa libido.</l>
                     <l>Criſpa tamen cunctas exercet cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore in uno,</l>
                     <l>Deglubit, fellat, molitur per utram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que cavernam,</l>
                     <l>Nequid inexpertum fruſtra haec moritura relinquat.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:55561:49"/>Where is Wantonneſs equal to that deſcribed by <hi>Petronius</hi> in a Woman? <hi>Junonem meam iratam habeam, ſi me unquam virginem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minerim; nam infans cum paribus inquinata ſum, &amp; ſubinde prodeun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus annis majoribas me pueris ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicui, donec ad hanc aetatem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veni.</hi> What wantonneſs in this age ever anſwered that of <hi>Meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lina?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ziphil.</note> 
                  <hi>quae efficiebat ut multae in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio viris ſuis praeſentibus ac viden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus cum adulteris coirent.</hi> What <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſatis</hi> was author of his Sons inceſt with his own Siſter in this age?
<note place="margin">Plut. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Where has Proſtitution been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged or promoted by a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and Law? If in this, as in all ages, ſomething be amiſs, what has this man to do to upbraid the times, being neither Divine nor Magiſtrate, to whom the correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Vices in any kind might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long? for though the words are taken out of the Preface of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he that with applauſe tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:55561:49"/>them, makes their Sordid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as much his own, as they were before the Authors that firſt writ them. And truly 'tis no marvel that men of light Principles ſhould be of looſe Tongues. He firſt tells us, in this age we have loſt Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, we underſtand not Phyſick, and now we fail in Sobriety and Cood manners.
<note place="margin">Pag 62.</note> After this large Preface, which hath given us the diverſion of two leaves, he falls upon a diſcourſe by what means <hi>the Venereal and Scorbutick Miaſms have gained ground in the world,</hi> to wit, by Carnal Contact, ill Cures, accidental Contagion, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary Propagation and Lactati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and is large upon every one of theſe heads. To what purpoſe all this is, and how it will ſerve his turn, I ſee not, except to uſher in their complication with other Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, which is the ſubject of his next Chapter, as I touched before. The Propagation of this <hi>Lues</hi> by
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:55561:50"/>Carnal Contact he paſſeth over to inſiſt upon a truth <hi>of much impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to be laid open for the ſecurity of mankind,</hi> viz. <hi>That after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting that folly with an unwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom perſon, though there appear no ſign nor ſymptom of a Diſeaſe for the preſent, yet it may lie latent and lurk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the body many years before it make any diſcovery of it ſelf, either in its own noture, or in the diſguiſe of other diſeaſes.</hi> And in another place tells you,
<note place="margin">Pag. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that it may be in the Father, lie quiet in the Son, and at laſt diſcover it ſelf in the Grandchild: and whatever he ſaith of the Pox, he would have you underſtand of the Scurvy alſo. This he proves from proſtituted Women, who having long lived in that wicked courſe, have infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many others without being pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy to any ilneſs in themſelves. In which Aſſertion he begs two things which are impoſsible for him to prove; firſt that thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:55561:50"/>were not privy to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of any Infection in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, notwithſtanding they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently enough might ſay they were not. For truly 'tis not hard to believe, that thoſe perſons that will lie with their Bodies in thoſe unjuſtifiable ways, will alſo lie with their Tongues when 'tis for their advantage, either to make themſelves appear more innocent, or their Copeſmates more confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Secondly that the Infection given to ſo many perſons hath proceeded from a Diſeaſe long la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, or perhaps one newly taken. I much fear, that Men and Women ſo given, keep not themſelves ſo conſtantly to the ſame perſon, that they can tell either when they give or take Infection, till by the ſuccedaneous effects it diſcovers it ſelf. Something more reaſonable might have been urged for him, were he able or any other to prove, that thoſe hundreds infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:55561:51"/>as he ſaith, by the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Woman, had never touched any other from whom they might poſsibly as well take it, as from her that did not know her ſelf infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. From this he paſſeth to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the teaſons <hi>why ſome that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe that wickedneſs, moſt of their days ſeem ſound even to old age;</hi> and there gives you a large tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript out of one he calls Dr. <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell,</hi> which being no may material, though in ſome things not true, I leave to the conſideration of thoſe whoſe time and leiſure will give them the liberty of a more ſerious examination of this Writers extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancies. Onely let me remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, he omits the main cauſe why men guilty of that wickedneſs eſcape ſound, <hi>viz.</hi> their frequent taking Phyſick for the expelling that Contagion they ſuſpect may lie in their bodies, though they find it not in any effect. And as he directs me what here I have ſpoken
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:55561:51"/>of the <hi>Lues Venerea,</hi> may be alſo underſtood of the Scurvy, <hi>mutatis mutandis;</hi> onely by the way let it be obſerved, that he conceives the Contagion of the French Diſeaſe leſs apt to be communicated than that of the Scurvy; for <hi>pag.</hi> 65. <hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi> he gives you many reaſons why ſome ſinners in one kind are not at all, or know not themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected; but in the Scurvy he tells you pag. 75. <hi>That whereever either of the mates is Scorbutically tainted, the other never ſcapes, but catches the taint more or leſs, &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty boldly aſſerted; <hi>Never ſcapes!</hi> What Aphoriſm of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> that he ſo much carps at, is ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral? yet this Pigmy muſt be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, or he will take it ill, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon and without experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when <hi>Hippocrates</hi> cannot up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both. Pray why may not thoſe reaſons taken from the difference of Conſtitution, the difference of Temper, the ſtrength of the Body,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:55561:52"/>uſed by him for aſſoiling men of the Pox, be uſed here in the Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, ſince by himſelf they are ſo near of kin? Or let him tell me what difference there is between <hi>not being,</hi> and <hi>not being diſcovered in its own colours, but in the garb of ſome other diſeaſe.</hi> Pray how ſhall one know that any Diſeaſe, that appears in its own garb, hath any of the Scorbvtical taint in it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept there be alſo ſome Scorbutical colours appear? unleſs he would have my faith as large as his, to wit, that whereever the one Mate <hi>is Scorbutically tainted, the other never eſcapes;</hi> for then whatever Diſeaſe may be, we are ſure the Scorbute is with it. But we have a caution here to check any oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to this, <hi>viz.</hi> Let him firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <hi>the courſe of things</hi> before he oppoſe it; ſo that his Anſwer is ready, Dr. <hi>Twyſden</hi> oppoſeth this, but he hath not obſerved the courſe of things. Pray, Sir, what
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:55561:52"/>courſe, or what things do you mean? they are both of very large extent, and you know <hi>Dolus ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatur in univerſalibus.</hi> I conceive the courſe of things to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved muſt be ſomething concerning the diſeaſe of the Scurvy, or elſe you ſpeak not <hi>ad idem.</hi> If in that Diſeaſe, then what period of it is moſt obſervable, or to be taken notice of? The Beginning cannot, for you ſay <hi>pag.</hi> 75. ſometime it diſcovers not it ſelf at all, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs nor the ending cannot of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes, for it ſometimes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers not it ſelf (you ſay) in its own colours, but in the garb of other Diſeaſes; and the diſcovery of it ſelf in its own colours, and in the garb of other Diſeaſes, are by you contradiſtinguiſhed: ſo that except when it diſcovers it ſelf in its own colours, which ſometimes happens not, it cannot be obſerved at all; and therefore that Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, either altogether, or in the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:55561:53"/>greateſt meaſure, is uſeleſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable. For my part, I have been for ſome time an obſerver of Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, both in their beginning, growth, and termination, and muſt agree with you, that the Scurvy is very frequently at the beginning or end of moſt Chronical ſickneſſes in our Iſland-bodies, and that the <hi>Lues</hi> is likewiſe very general, but cannot ſubſcribe to that Opinion, That their Infection is ſo catching, that all the World muſt needs be infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at ſo eafie a rate without Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tact, by the Emanation of I know not what Effluviums, inviſible Atoms or Bodikins, as our <hi>M. N.</hi> loves to call them,
<note place="margin">Pag. 99.</note> 
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 97. (rather than a ſubtil Vapour, which being ſucked in by our breath, may poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the body though it operate not preſently:) whenas he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines not their Sphere of Activity, nor at what diſtance their noxious qualities ſhall ceaſe. <hi>Sennertus</hi> in reckoning the manner of the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butical
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:55561:53"/>Contagion ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Med Prac. ti. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>part.</hi> 5. <hi>ca.</hi> 3.</note> Indeed it may be taken <hi>per ſemen &amp; ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem maternum, vel lacte inſtillari, aut alio modo per contactum &amp; conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſationem, pocula (ſcil.) aegrotantium uſu in bibendo praecipuè inquinata; oſcula etiam,</hi> ut nonnullis placet, <hi>aut aerem exhalationibus, expirationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; foetidis halitibus, aegrorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum inſpiratione attractum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municari poteſt.</hi> Here you ſee is but a <hi>nonnullis placet</hi> when the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication comes either by Kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, which is a Contact, or by the noxious Vapours taken in with the breath. Nay further, <hi>Cenſent etiam nonnulli per Venerem communicari poſſe Scorbutum, ſi (ſcil.) vir cum foemin â Scorbutica, fluxu albo labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante, concubuerit.</hi> You ſee here is but a <hi>Cenſent nonnulli,</hi> and then too a Circumſtance required which ſeldom falls out, that Men or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have any Communication when the Woman is ſo diſpoſed. So far you ſee is this learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:55561:54"/>from <hi>M. N.</hi> his confident Aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veration, That whereever either of the Mates is Scorbutically taint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the other never ſcapes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>You have thus heard the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Sennertus;</hi> in <hi>Foreſtus</hi> I find nothing at all touching the Contagiouſneſs of this Diſeaſe; perhaps he hath miſtaken his words, as he hath the ſenſe of <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nertus, Horſtius,</hi> and <hi>Reuſnerus.</hi> But becauſe I would uſe him with all civility, let us examine what their Opinion is touching the Contagion of the <hi>Lues Venerea</hi> at a diſtance. But there is an unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate rub lies here in his way, which he well knows not how to balk,
<note place="margin">Pag. 128.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Sennertus</hi> in other places of his book is ſo groſs, as to deny its Communicableneſs at a diſtance, as other Contagions are, &amp;c. I wiſh he had ſhewed us thoſe places where he ſaith, that Contagion may be taken without Contact. I am ſure where he
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:55561:54"/>handles the Queſtion purpoſely, he determines the contrary: <hi>Hoc tamen concedi non poteſt, quod ſicut peſtis per aerem &amp; loca diſſita ad alios transferri poteſt; ita etiam Lues Venerea communicari poſſit. Experientia enim quotidiana teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Medicos &amp; alios multos cum infectis hâc lue familiariter conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſari, nec tamen ab iis infici. De Lue Ven. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>part.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 503. <hi>edit. Venetianae. Foreſtus</hi> is of the ſame opinion, <hi>lib.</hi> 32. <hi>obſerv.</hi> 2. <hi>Itaque Lues Venerea contagioſus eſt morbus, non ſponte intimó<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> corporis vitio, ſed attactu ſolo contrahendus:</hi> then tells you of a Prieſt, that was <hi>adeo facie deturpatum, ut leproſus videre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; carcinomate totius faciei in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus;</hi> who being drunk, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a handſom Maid dancing with her Companions, kiſt her againſt her will, <hi>&amp; ſolo oſculo eâdem lue infecit.</hi> Certainly here was a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tact, and in all likelyhood he hung ſo long upon her lips, to leave filth
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:55561:55"/>enough there to beget that diſeaſe, without having recourſe to theſe Bodikins and Atoms, which muſt infect at a diſtance by the <hi>vehicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum</hi> of the Air and I know not what <hi>medium.</hi> You thus ſee the Opinion of <hi>Sennertus</hi> and <hi>Foreſtus,</hi> of the ſame Opinion he is forced to confeſs <hi>Fernelius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 126. &amp; 127.</note> 
                  <hi>though his wit is in many other things divine, flies ſo low a pitch concerning the conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſneſs of this diſeaſe, as to place it onely in humour and dull contact.</hi> Aurelius Minadous <hi>tells you, it ought not to be defined by Quality, but by name of a Bodily Subſtance, and that it ſo paſſeth from body to bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by contact.</hi> A man would have thought theſe Authors had been plain enough, and I thought of Learning enough to expreſs their own ſenſe in ſignificant words, but it ſeems they were deceived, and we too; for as to <hi>Fernelius</hi> he tells you, <hi>that in another place he ſpeaks plainly to our ſenſe,</hi> and quotes him
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:55561:55"/>
                  <hi>De morb. contagioſis cap.</hi> 14. he ſhould have done well to have told us a piece of news we are as yet ſtrangers to, where <hi>Fernelius</hi> writes fourteen Chapters <hi>de morbis contagioſis.</hi> But I will let that paſs, ſince the good man means well, and would have ſaid <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>de abdit. rerum cauſis,</hi> where he hath one Chapter <hi>de morbis conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioſis,</hi> the place he quotes is (in the laſt Edition put out by <hi>Hackius,</hi> 1645.) <hi>pag.</hi> 212. where beſides his falſe tranſlation of his words, <hi>quod dum vident ſymptomata haec omnia, cum humoris cujuſdam vitio inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare,</hi> nihil praeter humorem ineſſe putant. Which he renders, <hi>they think of nothing but humour;</hi> whereas the Author means, they think there is no other matter in the diſeaſe, than the peccancy of that humour, and do not careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſearch whether any thing elſe be latent under the cover of that humour ſo peccant, to wit, that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:55561:56"/>Contagious quality he then treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of; for I never before read, that <hi>ſubeſſe</hi> ſignified <hi>to prevail.</hi> But I ſhall let that paſs, and onely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that in that whole Chapter there is no one word to contradict what he ſaid before touching the <hi>Lues Venerea,</hi> but in his whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe inſtances the Contagion to come by Contact, and not <hi>per acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem ad diſtans.</hi> So <hi>Sennertus,</hi> whoſe words before cited, <hi>Cenſent nonnulli per Venerem, &amp;c. ſi (ſeil.) vir cum foeminâ Scorbuticâ, fluxu albo laborante,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>concubuerit:</hi> he tells you <hi>Sennertus</hi> is very poſitive, where his words are, <hi>Cenſent non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulli, Some think.</hi> Next by lying with a Scorbutick Woman, or with one that hath the <hi>Fluor albus:</hi> where doth he find <hi>(or)</hi> in the Text? <hi>Sennertus</hi> puts them both together, as if in the judgment of thoſe <hi>nonnulli</hi> 'twere not enough to lie with a Scorbutick Woman, but ſhe muſt likewiſe have that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:55561:56"/>diſeaſe upon her, to make the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion to paſs from one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: where is now the <hi>ſpeaking home</hi> of <hi>Fernelius,</hi> or <hi>poſitiveneſs</hi> of <hi>Sennertus?</hi> or what elſe is this but a corruption of Authors, and ſtraining their words contrary to their ſenſe or meaning? Yet that I may do him no wrong, though the foregoing Authors are not of his Opinion, yet <hi>Zacutus Luſitanus,</hi> the learned Jew, is otherwiſe minded. In his <hi>Praxis admiranda, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv.</hi> 125. he gives an Example out of <hi>Manardus</hi> his Epiſtles, of one troubled with an <hi>Ophthalmia Gallica,</hi> who infected his ſervant that waited upon him with the ſame diſeaſe; and therefore ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves that that Diſeaſe is contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous at a diſtance. Our <hi>M. N.</hi> ſhould have done well to have likewiſe taken notice of <hi>Sennertus</hi> his Anſwer to this Obſervation; firſt, that there is no Example but this of <hi>Manardus;</hi> ſecondly, that a
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:55561:57"/>ſimple <hi>Ophthalmia</hi> is infectious, and therefore a Venerate may more likely. He might likewiſe have obſerved, that this Servant was always about him, wiped off his ſweat, and undoubtedly dreſſed and waſhed his Eyes; ſo that here was, if not a direct, yet very near to a Contact. Beſides, the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Eyes are more likely to be Contagious, than thoſe that have their ſeat in any other part of the Body; becauſe, whether Sight be performed by the intromiſsion of <hi>ſpecies</hi> from the Object, or by emiſsion of Rays from the Eye, or both, it muſt of neceſsity be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Eye doth receive Rays, or elſe one Eye could not ſee another, where one is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the object to the other. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, 'tis to be taken notice of, that this is <hi>in praxi admirandâ,</hi> and ſo much out of the common rode. Laſtly, 'tis much to be feared that this Servant had got the diſeaſe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:55561:57"/>ſome other way, but was glad to put off the guilt of his fault by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to this of Infection. Well, but it cannot be denied that there paſs <hi>effluvia</hi> out of the body, <hi>atoms, bodikins,</hi> as he calls them,
<note place="margin">Pag. 141.</note> not a Spiritual ſubſtance; yet <hi>pag.</hi> 128. he tells you out of <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nertus,</hi> they are a Spirit or Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ſubſtance, a thing of ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til a nature, that it can make its own way through bodies without the help of immediate contact. If this laſt Aſſertion be true, the firſt cannot, and ſo farewell his Atoms and Bodikins, for certainly they cannot paſs through bodies any way, nothing but a Spirit can pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate Dimenſions. Bodies or Bodikins, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, call them as you will, differ onely in Majority and Minority, and ſo can enter in at the Pores onely, and no other ways. Well, however 'tis manifeſt ſuch Emanations there are, (and he is copious in proving
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:55561:58"/>what no man denies) as in the Plague, Spotted Fevers, Small Pox, Leproſie, Itch, and the like: if ſo, then he wiſhes ſome tolerable rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon were produced why they deny it in reference to the Pocky conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.
<note place="margin">Pag. 129</note>
                  <note place="margin">See <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, cap.</hi> 7. <hi>fol</hi> 28. Where he ſhews his opinion to be, that this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe can not be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tact.</note> Since the reaſon given by them, that the diſeaſe is lodged in a ſlow dull viſcous matter, doth not pleaſe him, I will endeavour to ſatisfie him with ſome other. I would firſt tell him after his own language, that the Atoms or Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxes that come from the Pocky body are of another figure than the Empty parts in the texture of the body, and ſo cannot enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. Perhaps the Effluxes that come from the ſound body are more and ſtronger than thoſe that come from the infected, and ſo purifie the Air, that it ſhall not be a <hi>vehiculum</hi> for the Contagion; as we ſee a Perfume will deſtroy a Stink. Whether theſe reaſons are true or not, is not material; I am
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:55561:58"/>ſure, according to his Principles, they are ſpecious, and are ſufficient Anſwers <hi>ad hominem,</hi> if they be not <hi>ad rem,</hi> and are urged by me to let him ſee how fallacious that way of Argumentation is, which is drawn from the application of Reaſon from one thing to another, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Experience. 'Twere a ſtrange way of arguing the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, which is a black heavy ſtone, of ſuch a bigneſs and weight, will take up a pound of Iron; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every Loadſtone of that big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will have the ſame virtue, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Truth and Experience. Juſt ſo 'tis with him; the Plague, &amp;c. is infectious, and the Conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion paſſeth from one body to another, without any immediate contact; therefore every Diſeaſe that is infections, as the Pox and Scurvy are, muſt do ſo too. Nay, he has the boldneſs to improve this Notion ſo high, as to tell us,
<note place="margin">Pag 130.</note> no man never ſo innocent can be
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:55561:59"/>ſecure that he is ſound: A Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine every way pernicious and unſafe; for the innocent, it makes them upon every light occaſion doubtful and ſuſpicious of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; the guilty, bolder and more impudent, being fitted with this lie in their mouth, However I am now tainted, 'tis not by my own fault, but the fault of my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Nurſe, or any other I have ſeen or converſed withall; endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring by this cheat to vindicate their own Credits in the world. And thus this miſerable <hi>flagellum ſcortatorum</hi> is made an Arrow to wound the innocent and excuſe the guilty, who will be always ready to caſt their diſeaſe <hi>upon that fine way of communication</hi> M.
<note place="margin">Pag. 97</note> N. <hi>hath taught them, which ſuits not with the conceit of a brain that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures every thing by the groſs</hi> Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ties men to in the Schools, who teach men that Infection may be by Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:55561:59"/>qualities inſinuating them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Air; whereas in truth they are infected by inviſible indiviſible Atoms corporeal ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluxes, as he ſaith Dr. <hi>Flud</hi> in his <hi>Moſaick Philoſophy,</hi> and Sir <hi>Kenelm Digby</hi> in his <hi>Diſcourſe at Montpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> have made manifeſt, with ſome others. How far theſe Examples will warrant the efflux of Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Atoms; or whether the ſame effects may not follow from the impacting incorporeal qualities, and the dulneſs of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, I ſhall have fitter oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to diſcourſe of hereafter; and I doubt not to ſhew, that this anciently-confuted and now late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-revived Philoſophy, of making Atoms the beginning of all Bodies, and their flying up and down <hi>in vacuo</hi> not to be without great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, and probably not true. This that hath been ſaid I conceive abundantly ſufficient to clear that part of his diſcourſe concerning
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:55561:60"/>the Propagation of the <hi>Lues Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea</hi> and Scorbute by accidental Contagion, Hereditary Propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Lactation, by all which ways I admit thoſe diſeaſes may be transferred from one to another; but deny, that either of them are ſo general as he would infer, or that they are transferred by ſuch an infection at diſtance, as the Plague, Malignant Fevers, and ſome others, but muſt be got by Contact, or very near and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Converſation.</p>
               <p>There reſt now onely to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine his ſecond cauſe, to wit, their Propagation by the ill-curing of them both. For my part, I ſhall never riſe up a Champion to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the ill-curing of any diſeaſe, much leſs either of them named; onely I would have him remember that of the Poet,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Carpere vel noli noſtra, vel ede tua.</hi> He juſtly condemns the going for cure to any Pretender,
<note place="margin">Pag. 76.</note> amongſt
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:55561:60"/>which number I reckon all Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanks, or ſuch as take upon them the Practice of Phyſick without lawful Warrant thereunto; and then runs over the ordinary Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, firſt of Iſſues, where by the way he ſhould do well to obſerve his inadvertency, in calling this age by exprobration <hi>an iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing age;</hi> for if the Pox be ſo general, and this be one kind of cure, though it be but the Poor-Whores cure, certainly he ought not to blame the Age for taking any courſe to cure their Maladies. Then comes <hi>Mercurial <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguent, Mercurial Cinabar fume by Saliva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and inveighs againſt them all; notwithſtanding he cannot but know they have been all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfully uſed by skilful men, and in unskilful mens hands the beſt Remedies will not ſucceed. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, he forgets the Method uſed by <hi>Fernelius</hi> and moſt others by Sudorifick Potions, made with
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:55561:61"/>
                  <hi>Lignum ſanctum, Sarſaparill, Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, &amp;c.</hi> He touches not upon <hi>Quercetans</hi> Method in his <hi>Conſilium pro Lue Venerea:</hi> Whether he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove theſe ways better than any by Mercury, I know not, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath any better of his own. 'Tis much to condemn all the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians in the world, and then leave us in the dark. Out with it, Man, tell the World if you know any better than others do: till then give us leave to think this onely an artifice to cry up your ſelves to the defamation of others, this is uſual with the reſt of your Gang, <hi>Manwairing, Odowd,</hi> and others, who pretend great things, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal what they are. In the Scurvy likewiſe he inveighs againſt Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Specificks, and that ordinary way by which we find by daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience that diſeaſe cured, if Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious men deal with them. He blames the uſe of Pills, Infuſions, Powders, Electuaries reputed Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:55561:61"/>and tells you, in all the <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macopoeus</hi> he cannot pick out one Compoſition proper to purge Scorbutical Humours in ſo gentle and effectual manner as they ought to be: What if there be not? Doth not he know, that every Phyſician is able to be his own Pharmacopoeiſt, and that thoſe Books are rather made for the uſe of Apothecaries and Surgeons than them? But let us ſee; what thinks he of the <hi>Pilulae macri,</hi> of the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tareae Quercetani,</hi> of the <hi>Sal Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chleariae, Abſinthii,</hi> and the reſt? Cannot a Maſs be made out of theſe proper enough to purge Scorbutick Humours? Pray, Sir, bleſs us with ſomething of your own, that we may judge of your Abilities, and owe our Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to you.</p>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <p>I have thus done with the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentative part of his book, and have ſhewed his fallacious ways of Argumentation throughout. Firſt, I have ſhewed that the nature of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:55561:64"/>Man, Beaſts, Plants, Herbs, Fruits, and all things conducing to the nouriſhment of Man, are of the ſame nature; and therefore Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, at leaſt thoſe that were known to the Ancients, are not altered in their nature, nor the Method in the curing of them altered. That the diſcovery of new Remedies, if any have been, do not take away the virtue of thoſe that were known and practiſed before; but both may be good and ſtand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and that my Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> and thoſe other Worthy perſons that have encouraged men to make further ſearch into the things of Nature, and thoſe Noble perſons that have written and ſtill labour in Experimental Philoſophy, do not do it to diſparage the Ancients, but ſearch into the Reaſons of the works of Nature, and diſcover new Truths, and eſtabliſh the old by new Confirmations. I have in the ſecond place ſhewed that the Pox
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:55561:64"/>and Scurvy, which this Author much inſiſts upon, were not new diſeaſes in themſelves, though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps lately brought into <hi>Europe:</hi> that their Cures were found out by and upon the Foundation of the ancient Method, which is able to furniſh a Phyſician not onely with means to find out the ſeat of any diſeaſe, but alſo to apply ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate remedies thereunto. I have ſhewed in the third place, that the Complication of Diſeaſes cannot alter the general Method of curing them, though it may cauſe a variation in the application of Remedies. That the variation of Remedies, according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Diſeaſes in their Complica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is the Office of a Phyſician, who ties not himſelf to any Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies delivered in <hi>Pharmacopoeus,</hi> but ordering them <hi>pro re nata;</hi> and that 'tis impoſsible to give any ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Method to cure any one complicated Diſeaſe, as it is lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:55561:65"/>in <hi>Peter;</hi> becauſe never any ſuch Diſeaſe came twice alike in all circumſtances, nor can any Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be found out (I am confident is not by this Undertaker) that ſhall have that effect. What the Chymiſts ſpeak of their <hi>Sulphur fixum,</hi> and their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſale ſolvens,</hi> which ſhall have that power; and alſo with ſome other help of Art ſhall ſix an imperfect Metall into Gold: as I will not deny the truth of it, ſo will I ſuſpend my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment till I ſhall be better convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. For all other Remedies, in the preparation whereof Chymiſts have laboured, I ſhall give them my ready thanks with much grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of mind for their pains: they have many of them made their Medicines and Preparations publick, and daily uſe is made of them; when this unknown <hi>M. N.</hi> makes us partakers of any of his, bet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er than what we know, I ſhall readily return him my due thanks;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:55561:65"/>but muſt not believe ſome few moneths ſtudy of Chymiſtry under Mr. <hi>Johnſon,</hi> ſet up by the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of <hi>London</hi> for their uſe, have made him ſo perfect an Artiſt as to know more than his Teachers in that Art. The pretending to be Maſters of great and univerſal Remedies, and conceal what they are, (a practice now uſed by <hi>Odowd, Manwairing,</hi> and ſome others) is a thing ſo unworthy a Scholar, that I would not have this Author ſo like a Mountebank in any thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Examination of the Sixth Chapter.</head>
               <p>THus have I with all poſsible brevity run over his firſt Five Chapters, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed contain moſt of what is Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentative in his book; I come to the Sixth, which begins with a recapitulation of what he had
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:55561:66"/>formerly proved. In the former we have had a taſte of his Philoſophy and Logick, we ſhall now try his Logick alone, and ſee whether the Concluſion drawn from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes now laid down be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to thoſe of his firſt Chapter, where he argues thus:
<list>
                     <item>If Diſeaſes are altered in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wholly from what they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently were; Then</item>
                     <item>New Indagations, new Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, new Cures muſt be found, Phyſick and Surgery muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built from the very foundation.</item>
                     <item>But Diſeaſes are wholly altered in their nature.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore in his ſixth Chapter he argues thus:
<list>
                     <item>If there be now introduced in Men and Diſeaſes as it were another nature; Then</item>
                     <item>The former Rules calculated for Curation from other Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or from Cauſes leſs impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, are almoſt, if not quite, out of doors.</item>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:55561:66"/>
                     <item>But Men and Diſeaſes are as it were altered in their nature.</item>
                     <item>Therefore the former Rules, &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Quo teneam tandem mutantem Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tea nodo?</head>
               <p>In the beginning of his book his premiſes were univerſal and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, in this place they are limited and particular. At the firſt there was a total alteration of Nature, now a partial, perhaps at the later end we ſhall find none at all.</p>
               <p>But this is not all; we muſt find other infirm parts of his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Certainly <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> as dull as he was, would never have thus concluded, nor any man that had read or well underſtood his Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyticks, or the reaſon why they are ſo called. Where he firſt ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Concluſion, which is the <hi>Res ignota,</hi> as known and true; and then infers it <hi>ex veris &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsis:</hi> ſo that if there be any thing in the premiſes which is not <hi>verum
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:55561:67"/>&amp; conceſſum,</hi> then can the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be never truly inferred, and the thing ſought concluded. Now (Sir) would I gladly ſee how you infer the conſequence of your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor;</hi> what have we to do to leap from Nature to Cauſes? You ought thus to have aſſumed; If there be now introduced as it were in Men and Diſeaſes another na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; Then Curations found out for Men and Diſeaſes, which now are as it were of another nature than formerly, muſt be as it were changed. But Men and Diſeaſes are as it were altered in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in this Syllogiſm both the ſequel of the <hi>Major</hi> and <hi>Minor</hi> are neither of them granted; for there may be a partial and circumſtantial alteration of a Diſeaſe, and if you will of a Man, without any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all of the Nature of that Diſeaſe in its Cauſe, or the Nature of the Man in its Cauſe. (But cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:55561:67"/>when we can believe the Nature of Man can be altered in its Cauſe, the next ſtep will be to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he may be altered in his <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> too.) May not a Fever that invades a Pocky or Scorbutick body have the ſame Cauſe, though in reſpect of the Complication there may be a partial alteration in the Diſeaſe, and conſequently a circumſtantial variation in the Cure? I admit that the Cures of the Ancients were built upon the conſiderations of Diſeaſes in their Cauſes, but muſt not grant that the ſame Cauſe may not produce a Diſeaſe ſomewhat altered in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. So that if it were granted him, which he hath no way proved, and is not true, that Diſeaſes anciently known are at all altered in their Nature; yet would it not follow, that they were alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their Cauſes. The whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument brought into form ought to run thus:
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:55561:68"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Major.</hi> If there be now introduced in Men and Diſeaſes as it were a new Nature, from rebellion and alterations not known to the Ancients in their Cauſes, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of ſo fully as they ought to be by the later Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians; Then</item>
                     <item>The Rules of Curation calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated for Men and Diſeaſes, now as it were of new natures from thoſe alterations, not known to the Ancients in their Cauſes, or taken notice of ſo fully as they ought to be by the later Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, muſt be as it were altered and changed.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Minor.</hi> But there is now introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in Men and Diſeaſes as it were a new Nature from malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and alterations not known to the Ancients in their Cauſes, or taken notice of ſo fully as they ought by later Phyſicians.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Concluſion.</hi> Therefore the Rules of Curation calculated for Men
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:55561:68"/>and Diſeaſes, now as it were of new natures, from alterations not known to the Ancients in their Cauſes, or taken notice of ſo fully as they ought to be by the later Phyſicians, muſt be as it were altered and changed.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis evident here, that the whole ſtrength of his Argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion depends upon the introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a new Nature into Men and Diſeaſes; ſo that till that be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, 'tis not at all material to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the Cauſes of this change, nor whether the Ancients knew them or not: but certainly he is very far from having proved either a total or a partial alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Men or Diſeaſes in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>All Ages have produced as great mortality and as great rebellion in Diſeaſes as this, and Complications with other Diſeaſes as dangerous. What Plague was ever more
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:55561:69"/>ſpreading or dangerous than that writ of by <hi>Thucidides,</hi> brought out of <hi>Attiea</hi> into <hi>Peloponneſus?</hi> What Complication now cauſed by the preſence of the Pox or Scurvy in a ſick body, can make a greater al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration in any diſeaſes, than the Complication of the like diſeaſe with the Leproſie heretofore? Doth he not believe there is as great a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the bloud by the Leproſie as the Pox? yet thoſe diſeaſes were cured by the ancient Method, why not theſe? So that for ought I ſee we need not be put to the neceſsity of <hi>eſtabliſhing new Doctrines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 204.</note> 
                  <hi>new Methods and Rules of Curation, agreeable to the new frame of Humane nature, and to the new</hi> Phaenomena <hi>of Diſeaſes.</hi> The old Notions and old Remedies may be good enough; not that I ſhall diſcourage him or any man for increaſing the <hi>Materia Medica</hi> with any new piece of Knowledge, but diſlike they ſhould pretend to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:55561:69"/>what they have not, (as many do) to the diſhonour of others far more knowing than themſelves.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being conſidered, this Chapter is not ſo hard but it may be read over without a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuke or ſpelling-book, and by thoſe that have ſet up their reſt without any new going to ſchool by them;
<note place="margin">Pag. 206.</note> and yet <hi>the ſaying of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Celſus the Plagiary of Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> may be true too, <hi>Vix ulla perpetua praecepta ars medicinalis recipit:</hi> which ſaying hath not relation to the Method or Art, but to the Medicine and Perſon; for though general Precepts may be given <hi>curare morbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> they cannot be <hi>curare Petrum &amp; Paulum;</hi> and I dare confidently averre, that no man has been loſt by the adhering to the Precepts of Phyſick, though ſome may have by the miſapplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, in reducing them to uſe and practice; whereas hundreds daily are caſt away by the prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:55561:70"/>uſe of Remedies, eſpecially Chymical ones ſlovenly prepared by theſe Mountebanks, and as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>methodically appli'd at adventure.</p>
               <p>In his next Breach he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to draw to his Cauſe by the ſhoulders Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> whom he often quotes, and would fain induce the world to think him of his party; the paſſage he tells you is in his <hi>Experimental Philoſophy, part</hi> 2. <hi>eſſay</hi> 5. he ſhould have done well to have given us a little near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er gueſs at the place, for that Eſſay conſiſts of twenty large Chapters, near half the book, and I believe he hath particularly concealed it, leſt ſomething might be found not to make for him. Perhaps that Phyſician might think that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod fair, which in it ſelf was not, and the party not killed by a fair but a foul Method. But this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman would from hence have us look upon Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> as an Enemy to Method; but pray hear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:55561:70"/>
                  <hi>Exper. Philoſ. part</hi> 2. <hi>eſſay</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. <hi>pag.</hi> 266. ſpeaking of the nature and cauſes of Diſeaſes he hath theſe words, Nor is the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of curing <hi>divers particular diſeaſes more ſettled and agreed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that depending chiefly upon the knowledge of thoſe cauſes, which as I was ſaying are controverted: 'Tis not that I am an enemy to Method in Phyſick, or an undervaluer of it; but I fear the generality of Phyſicians (for I intend not, nor need all along this Eſſay ſpeak of them all) have as yet but an imperfect Method, and have by the narrow principles they were taught in the Schools, been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded to change their Method ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the barren principles of the Peripatetick School, than to the full amplitude of Nature.</hi> You ſee with what caution this Learned Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man delivers his ſenſe: Firſt, the Method of curing <hi>divers particular diſeaſes,</hi> to wit, as they may be in <hi>Craſo</hi> or <hi>Celſus;</hi> not that the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:55561:71"/>Method of curing diſeaſes is unſettled. Secondly, that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not all but ſome Phyſicians, though perhaps what he ſaith may fall upon the greateſt part of them. Thirdly, that himſelf is no Enemy to Method, though its Precepts do not anſwer to the ſull ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Nature. What can be more cautelouſly laid down? What is here to favour a caſting away old Methods, erecting new Foundations, new Aphoriſms, and I know not what, which our <hi>M. N.</hi> drives at?. Touching his opinion of Chymiſts, and their coſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Chymical Medicines in ſlight caſes, ſee what he ſaith <hi>chap.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 147, 148, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 152. the words are too long to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, but in general he blames the Chymiſts as well in their unskilful preparations, as not dexterous ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of their Medicines; and is ſo far from tying up Phyſick to that Sphere onely, that he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:55561:71"/>many great Cures perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by ſimple Medicines taken from Vegetables and Animals, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Chymical preparation at all. As to that Noble Perſon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, I muſt tell the world I have had the honour to have been par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly acquainted with him now upwards of twenty years, that I know him to be a Scholar and Valuer of Learning where he meets it; he hath ſpent all his time from his very youth amongſt Men of Learning, and much of it in our Univerſities, and therefore I am ſure will give him little thanks that endeavours to bring him in as a Patron to thoſe that decry Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, Degrees, Learning, and Arts, endeavouring to bring in thereby Ignorance in the Profeſſors, and Contempt upon the Profeſsions themſelves. I ſhall further adde, I have frequently been in his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boratory, ſeen and been from him made partaker of many of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:55561:72"/>before the world knew them in Print, have received from his own hand not onely the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Preparations, but the Medicines themſelves, which I have often uſed with ſucceſs, and have returned to him ſome of my own, which he hath taken kindly from me. But in all the courſe of this my knowledge of him, have ever found him Free, of a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable and Noble nature, a Friend to Scholars, free from that arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance and pride of his Own Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge above Others; whoſe Pots and Glaſſes theſe petty fellows, who with ſo much boldneſs cry up themſelves, are not worthy to clean after him. To this he hath added the communication of many excellent Preparations and other Medicines; whereas this Writer, and many other of his Complices, pretend onely to a ſecret and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed kind of Knowledge. And in many other places of his book
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:55561:72"/>quotes this Noble Perſon very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the purpoſe, of which I ſhall take no further notice, the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter here by me knowingly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of him, being able to ſilence all Calumnies that by Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their own drawing out of his words, contrary to his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, may be pinn'd upon him; of which 'tis none of the leaſt that by this <hi>M. N.</hi> who in the quotation of that paſſage even now recited, leaves out the moſt material part of the ſentence he cites; firſt alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether leaving out that which gave a riſe to the diſcourſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Method of curing ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular diſeaſes was not perfectly ſettled, and then recites the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence he doth cite, lamely; for whereas Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> ſaith what may concern the generality of Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, (is not intended by him all along that Eſſay to be ſpoken of them all) this <hi>Parentheſis</hi> is left out, becauſe it made not for him, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:55561:73"/>ſtrook onely at ſuch who reſted upon the bare Phyſiology, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Phyſicians as well as others were wonted to be imbued in the Schools, <hi>pag.</hi> 236. <hi>part</hi> 2. without endeavouring to advance that knowledge by new accretions, and neglected the uſe of Specificks in diſeaſes, becauſe they found in them no ſenſible Evacuations of the Peccant humour. If the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of Phyſicians ſhould be of that mind, I ſhould blame them as much as he, but it appears he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves not that all are, and I thank God I know none that are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined; for my ſelf, I daily make uſe of Specificks when I know them, nor ever met in conſultation with any Learned perſon that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the uſe of them. I find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing material in this Chapter that hath not already been anſwered: the paſſage out of <hi>Hippocrates, pag.</hi> 217. that of <hi>Riverius</hi> learning of a Begger-woman the curing the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:55561:73"/>
                  <hi>Haemorrhoides,</hi> I approve well; nor will I refuſe to learn what I know not of any man; not that this Medicine was the Begger-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, for you may find it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for ſtopping Fluxes of bloud both in <hi>Matthiolus</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary upon <hi>Dioſcorides,</hi> and in <hi>Macaſius</hi> his <hi>Promptuarium:</hi> but 'tis not poſsible any Phyſician ſhould have ſuch a memory, to carry in his mind whatever he had read. I very well remember a Gentlewoman once told me, ſhe learnt of a Begger-woman that Hollihock flowers boiled in Milk would ſtop the <hi>Fluxus mulierum poſt partum;</hi> 'twas new to me then, but I have ſince found it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by many Authors for the like effect: and truly I have not yet been ſo happy to meet with any of thoſe Old Womens receipts, which I have not been able to trace where they had their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Theſe Country-women get
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:55561:74"/>the <hi>Country Houſwife,</hi> ſome Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Herbal, or the like, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time light of good things, which to thoſe that know them not paſs for their own.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 222. he enters into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of Humility: I joyn with him in that, and ſhall not onely commend his Converſation with thoſe that cure Horſes, but would adviſe the uſe of his and the reſt of that Gangs concealed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines upon thoſe creatures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ventured them upon Men, till the world were better acquainted with their Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or their Abilities there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p>I ſhould now give over this Chapter, did I not find it neceſſary once again to vindicate my Noble Friend Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> from the Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of this bold Aſſertor and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenuous perſon, who now <hi>pag.</hi> 226. mangling Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>'s words, endeavours to make him ſay, there
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:55561:74"/>is no need of Learning (commonly ſo called) to make a good Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian. I will tranſcribe his words though they are long. <hi>Pag.</hi> 394. <hi>And in the laſt place, Pyrophilus, I muſt advertiſe you not to expect that every one of the Remedies I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend ſhould be Phyſick and Phyſician too; I mean, that it ſhould of it ſelf ſuffice to perform the cures of thoſe diſeaſes againſt which it is commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For Medicines are but inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the hands of the Phyſician; and though they be never ſo well edg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and tempered, require a skilful hand to manage them: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I cannot but admire and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approve their boldneſs, that venture upon the practice of Phyſick, wherein it is ſo dangerous to commit errours, barely upon the confidence of having good Receipts. For though I dare not deny, but that he may proſperouſly practiſe Phyſick that either ignores or diſſents from the receiv'd Doctrine of the Schools, concerning the cauſes of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:55561:75"/>diſeaſes and ſome other Pathological particulars; yet I cannot but diſlike their boldneſs who venture to give active Phyſick either in intricate or acute diſeaſes, without at leaſt a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocrity of knowledge in Anatomy, and ſo much knowledge of the hiſtory of diſeaſes, as may ſuffice to inform them in a competent meaſure, what are the uſual ſymptoms of ſuch a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, what courſe Nature is wont to take in dealing with the peccant mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and what diſcernible alterations in the Patients body do commonly fore-run a Criſis, or otherwiſe the good or bad event of the diſeaſe.</hi> Then goes on and tells you, he will ſtand in need of a competent knowledge of the <hi>Materia Medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a,</hi> and the Method of compounding Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. Now then let the world judge what ingenuity there is in this Citation, as he has mangled it; and what he ſaith more than <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> ſaith in his Life put out by <hi>Plantius;</hi> nay, <hi>Avicenna</hi> himſelf
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:55561:75"/>ſaith as much, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Fen.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 8. <hi>edit. Venet.</hi> 1608. <hi>apud Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as,</hi> ſpeaking <hi>de ſubjecto Medicinae; Harum verò rerum quaedam ſunt, de quibus medico nihil aliud eſt agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, [niſi ut quid ſit tantùm eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiali formatione informet] &amp; utrum ſint vel non ſint, doctori ſapientiae phyſicalis credat:</hi> and ſo goes on to the end of that Chapter. By which it is evident from that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Arabian, that a Phyſician is not bound with too great ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſneſs to ſearch into every thing, the knowledge whereof may be uſeful, but not abſolutely neceſſary to him as a Practiſer. Of this rank I reckon the too ſcrupulous inquiry into the nature of all Plants, the too much wading into the niceties and new diſcoveries in Anatomy, of which, Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> well ſaith, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent knowledge is neceſſary; not that I diſcourage or diſlike the labours of thoſe that can afford themſelves liberty to ſpend all
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:55561:76"/>their time in theſe Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the increaſe of their own knowledge, and the great good of others, but would not have it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their excellent Abilities in the cure of Diſeaſes and viſiting Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, which is the main end of all their ſtudies. In this number I would alſo reckon the Doctrine of the Compoſition of Mixt bodies, the Combination of the four qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, Hot, Cold, Moiſt, and Dry; the Doctrine of Critical Days, Pulſes, Urines, and Temperaments, which is the ſubject of the reſt of his book; in which I hold it more ſafe for a man to reſt upon the Opinion of the Ancients, built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on great Reaſon and many years Experience in the curing diſeaſes by Remedies found out upon ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of thoſe things, though perhaps in every minute particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar not exactly true; than upon whimſies and conceits of our own, not built upon greater Reaſon and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:55561:76"/>leſs Experience, to overthrow the Method and Foundation of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick without firſt erecting another, upon which we may build with as much ſafety and aſſurance.</p>
               <p>I might here make a cloſe to his whole book, the reſt of his time and ink being ſpent moſt upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives againſt <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> perſons above the biting of his venemous tooth; and the firſt as to his Cavils againſt his Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms, Prognoſticks, &amp;c. ſo fully and learnedly vindicated by Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Sprackling,</hi> that when he or any of his Tribe ſhall give a ſolid Anſwer thereunto, he ſhall then ſee what more may be added up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſubject; onely let me adde this to the much materially ſaid by Doctor <hi>Sprackling,</hi> that he condemns ſome of them for their Plainneſs, in which he diſcovers his own Ignorance, not knowing that Aphoriſms are ſhort Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and therefore ought to be
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:55561:77"/>plain. But pray, Sir, is it not as plain, that <hi>totum eſt majus parte,</hi> that the whole is greater than a part; that if from equal you take away equal, the reſidue ſhall be equal, which may as well be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>? yet theſe were thought fit to be laid down by <hi>Euclide</hi> as previous to his <hi>Elements,</hi> and yet was never bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for their plainneſs: nay, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them we ſhould have been at a loſs, for many Demonſtrations both by <hi>Euclide, Archimedes,</hi> and others, made good onely <hi>per de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductionem ad impoſſibile.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in his next Chapter he is ſo bitter againſt the frigid notion of Four Elements, that we muſt away with them root and branch, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being heard what they can plead for themſelves, I ſhall enter into conſideration of the Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fition of Mixt bodies; and though I would not be underſtood to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend that Doctrine in every thing,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:55561:77"/>but onely that thoſe that make the <hi>principia corporum</hi> to be <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomi,</hi> and thoſe that make them Salt, Sulphur, Spirit, Water and Earth, either are the ſame with the four Elements, or, where they differ, are ſubject to as inextrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble difficulties as can be urged in allowing their compoſition to be from four Elements, Fire, Air, Water and Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An Examination of the Doctrin of the Elements, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Mixt Bodies.</head>
               <p>TO him that conſiders under what great obſcurities the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Philoſophers laboured to find out the cauſes and beginning of things, who being either whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deprived of the knowledge of the Creation, or but darkly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:55561:78"/>the Hiſtory of it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered indeed very anciently by <hi>Moſes,</hi> but by moſt of them either not ſeen or not believed, to wit, that there was an Omnipotent Power who was able of nothing to create all things, by the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual operation of his Word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring with his Spirit; <hi>He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and they were made: Thou ſendeſt forth thy Spirit and they were created.</hi> To him, I ſay, that conſiders theſe things, it will not at all ſeem ſtrange to find them ſometimes run into errors, which we ſee thoſe that come after them in this fertile Age of Learning, and deep ſearch into Natural Cauſes, cannot fully excuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of. Inſomuch that had we that ingenuity which might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly have been expected from us by our dead Predeceſſors, we ſhould rather render them their due honour, for many great Truths delivered by them to us,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:55561:78"/>when like our <hi>M. N.</hi> with too great preſumption and boldneſs, rail upon their perſons with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives, calling the Philoſophy of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> dull; the notion of four Elements, frigid; <hi>Galen,</hi> the great corrupter; <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his learned Book <hi>De Principiis,</hi> ſlighted; his Doctrine of Critical Days called as childiſh a conceit as was ever owned by any long beards, called the children of men. Without returning invectives againſt this Writer, who lies open enough to him that hath a mind, I ſhall onely with as much brevity as may be, propound the ſeveral opinions, as well of the ancient as modern Authors touching this matter, and with as much candor as I can lay them down, and then leave the Reader to judge where the moſt reaſon is.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not enter into the ſubtil ſpeculation <hi>de Materiâ primâ,</hi> an Abyſs fathomleſs, and in which
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:55561:79"/>all that have endeavoured to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate have rather loſt themſelves then found that out: and 'tis no wonder, for how can Man, who is not able to judge of any thing but under the Idea of ſomewhat hath fallen under ſome of his ſenſes, tell what that is that cannot poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly fall under any one of them? <hi>Plato, Pythagoras,</hi> and thoſe of their Sect, made the beginning of things to be what could not be comprehended either by ſenſe or imagination, but made it conſiſt in certain eternal and unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Ideas or Numbers. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> makes <hi>Privation</hi> to have the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a <hi>Principium;</hi> for having diſputed upon that ſubject, <hi>Ex ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilo nihil fit,</hi> he tells you, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: that is to ſay, That according to his opinion,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:55561:79"/>nothing could be ſimply made, <hi>ex non ente,</hi> yet <hi>per accidens</hi> it might; for out of Privation, which in it ſelf was nothing, having no exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, ſomething is made. <hi>Phyſ. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. Then after ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Here he tells you, That <hi>Hyle</hi> or <hi>Materia prima</hi> and Priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are different; and of theſe, that <hi>Hyle</hi> is a <hi>Non ens</hi> by accident, but Privation properly; that <hi>Hyle</hi> is near, and as it were a ſubſtance or exiſtence, but Privation by no means. Laſt of all ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phy. lib.</hi> 1 <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. That is, That <hi>Hyle</hi> is the firſt ſubject of every thing, out of which what ever hath being not by accident is begotten. By all which you may ſee how <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> was ſtreightned to extricate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:55561:80"/>in the buſineſs of the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of things. He found there was a neceſsity to admit in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſomething to be made out of nothing, and yet not ſeeing how that could be, tells you it could not be ſimply true, but true by accident, explains his meaning by Privation, which though it were in a manner <hi>non ens,</hi> yet gave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to ſomething that was, as the privation of one thing is the generation of another, where Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is but accidentally the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of an Entitie. Then after tells you, that <hi>Hyle</hi> is a <hi>Non ens per accidens,</hi> but Privation properly ſo. Why is <hi>Hyle</hi> a <hi>Non ens per acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens?</hi> Becauſe he could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend how, if it were admitted to be an Entitie, and have exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, there muſt not be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing precedent, which muſt be the matter of that matter, and ſo there would be a climbing <hi>in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinitum.</hi> All this I conceive pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:55561:80"/>from his not knowing the power of God to create all things of nothing, and that Maxim, <hi>Ex nihilo nihil fit,</hi> was onely true <hi>à parte poſt,</hi> not <hi>à parte ante.</hi> 'Tis true, ſince the Creation, nothing can be made by it ſelf, but muſt come from a ſeminal vertue by God's bleſsing given to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that various things might be produced according to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral kinds; but before the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it was not ſo. But the ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of theſe things being whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Metaphyſical, I ſhall ſo leave them, and refer thoſe that have a mind to wade beyond their depths in them to what <hi>Vaſques, Scotus, Suarez,</hi> and all the Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts have written upon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Yet withall let me adde this Obſervation, that both <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who in many things diſagreed, yet in this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, that from this <hi>Materia prima</hi> were produced the four
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:55561:81"/>Elements of Fire, Air, Water and Earth, <hi>Plato</hi> aſcribing to them their ſeveral forms.</p>
               <p>The next ſort of Philoſophers we are to deal with are <hi>Democri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Epicurus,</hi> and thoſe of that Sect. Not that I am ignorant that <hi>Democritus</hi> lived before the time of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> contemporary with <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and that <hi>Epicurus</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>Ariſtotle, Democritus, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedocles, Anaxagoras</hi> and <hi>Parme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nides</hi> lived about the 80 Olympi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ade, and were lookt upon as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of a different ſort of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, then what was generally by others of their age thought moſt probable and moſt received; ſome holding one opinion, ſome another concerning the beginning of things, as you may ſee them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in ſundry places in his Phyſicks, his Book <hi>de Coelo,</hi> and other of his Writings. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them all <hi>Democritus,</hi> or perhaps one ancienter then he,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:55561:81"/>
                  <hi>Leucippus,</hi> broach'd that opinion, that all things were at firſt made of Atoms, though I confeſs I find not that word uſed before the time of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> who flouriſhed much about the time of <hi>Ariſtotle:</hi> they maintained that the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of all things came from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms flying about <hi>in vacuo,</hi> and that by their motion &amp; concourſe all bodies were made. They a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed not well what to call them; ſome called them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, unities; others, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, little bodies; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>plena, &amp; denſa;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the firſt matter of all things. And <hi>Epicurus</hi> ſaith, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. That it was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an Atom, not becauſe it was the leaſt bodie, but becauſe it could not be divided, being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of vacuitie. See <hi>Gaſſend. Phyſ. ſect.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Then they farther added they were
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:55561:82"/>
                  <hi>aſpera, levia, rotunda, angulata, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata;</hi> rough, light, round, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, and hooked. <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells you, that <hi>Democritus</hi> allowed them magnitude and figure, and <hi>Epicurus</hi> allowed them weight; ſo that it ſeems they were both hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie and light. <hi>Vid. Lactan. de ira Dei, pag.</hi> 784. <hi>edit. Hacky,</hi> 1660. However, be they what they will, from theſe, as the beginning of all things, was the Univerſe made. This opinion ſeemed ſo unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that for nigh 2000 years it lay buried and forgotten, till at laſt it was revived by <hi>Gaſſendus,</hi> a learned Philoſopher and Divine, <hi>Regius Profeſſor</hi> of the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks at <hi>Paris,</hi> whom my ſelf had the honour particularly to know, and frequently converſe with there, and often about this ſubject; I found him a man very communicable, but to me would never declare his opinion to agree with that of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:55561:82"/>to write his Life and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, thought fit to propound fairly what might be ſaid on that ſubject. This opinion, in my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, labours under many and great improbabilities. Firſt, they admit of no firſt Cauſes beyond the ſphere of Nature, and are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted againſt by <hi>Lactantius</hi> as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers of Providence. They held there was no difference between <hi>Materia prima</hi> and <hi>Elementa:</hi> That Atoms were both, and had their beginning <hi>ab aeterno</hi> from no other cauſe but Nature or themſelves, againſt <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who affirms, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elementis eterna fieri impoſſibile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, They were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, little bodies, that they had figure and weight; ſo there was <hi>locatum,</hi> but there was no <hi>locus,</hi> for they did <hi>volitare in vacuo,</hi> for <hi>in vacuo</hi> there can neither be ſpace nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion, and a Body cannot be without both, neither can we have any other Idea of a Body,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:55561:83"/>but what we have of Space. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, <hi>in Vacuo</hi> there can be no terms of motion.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, There is leſs ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurditie to make <hi>maeximum divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibile</hi> the beginning of things then <hi>Minimum.</hi> Nature might as well make a great bodie of nothing, or let it be from eternitie, as make many little ones out of them to make one great one; for <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum</hi> and <hi>Minimum</hi> differ not ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifically, and divide a bodie into what particles you pleaſe, the matter is ſtill the ſame, and the magnitude would be the ſame, could you reſtore the figure, and a thing is called <hi>Maximum</hi> in reſpect of the matter, not the figure.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, There can be no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid reaſon given for the paſsion of any bodie from this Doctrin; for if the firſt Man were made from the voluntary concourſe of Atoms, they being impaſsible and eternal, why is not the <hi>compoſitum</hi> ſo too?
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:55561:83"/>There is in them no contrarietie, and ſo can be no fighting between contrarie qualities, which ſhould cauſe either pains or death, their difference being onely in figure. This argument is uſed by <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> in his book <hi>de naturâ hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manâ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. If a man be but one, that is to ſay, of one principle, he could not feel pain. <hi>Fernelius</hi> tells you in his Book <hi>de Elementis, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>His argumentis tanquam fuſtibus vis illa &amp; turbulenta con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſu atomorum immutabilium per inane volitantium in exilium rele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gata, &amp; de naturâ &amp; mundoque de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſa videri poſſit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his Phyſicks demonſtrates, that a <hi>continuum</hi> cannot be made of indiviſibles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in them there is nothing firſt nor laſt, in regard there are no parts; the Chapter is well worth reading over, and confuted by thoſe that think themſelves able to do it.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:55561:84"/>
               <p>Sixthly, How comes it that all things are made with ſo great or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, if they came by a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary concourſe of Atomes at firſt? why have we not ſtill the ſame things? An infinitie of Atoms can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be exhauſted, nor can any reaſon be given why there are not every day new Machines made equal to the frame of the world. Why need we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eeds of any thing? that which brought them at firſt may continue them ſtill. 'Tis ſtrange to think this <hi>Machina mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di</hi> could be made by a concourſe of Atoms, and yet we never ſaw a poor Cottage ſo made. Or at leaſt whence comes it to paſs, that ſome new concourſe of Atoms doth not disjoint, and put this already made out of frame?</p>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <p>To ſay that here is a tranſition from Mathematical to Phyſical lines, is but a meer <hi>effugium</hi> or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, for what ever is Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally true is Phyſically true too, if you take it under a Phyſical conſideration; and the line or Atom <hi>a c,</hi> take it under what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration or notion ſoever, will be ſtill ſhorter then <hi>a d c,</hi> and ſo <hi>a d c</hi> not the <hi>minimum diviſibile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, An Atom muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered under the notion of a Quantity, let it be the leaſt. But <hi>Diophantus</hi> will teach you <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Arithm. quaeſt.</hi> 33. that an Unit, that is to ſay, the leaſt quantity
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:55561:85"/>is in its own nature diviſible.</p>
               <p>To ſay that an Atom is diviſible in its own nature, but that nature never did proceed to the dividing it, is to ſpeak this not intelligible; for how is it poſsible to conſider a thing diviſible in its own nature, and yet not to have its beginning from ſomething leſs then it ſelf? Neither can you have any other Idea of it then as a thing extended, and ſo occupying a place.</p>
               <p>Perhaps it may be ſaid, that thoſe that aſſert the doctrine of Atoms are not ſo rigid as I make them, but will allow, that though all bodies are made of Atoms, yet they are made of fiery, aery, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and watry Atoms, and that from the diſcord of theſe all paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and death comes. If their meaning be this, we ſhall eaſily agree. The difference being onely verbal, they calling that an Atom which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calls an Element, then will not the notion of the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:55561:86"/>four Elements be ſo frigid as our <hi>M. N.</hi> makes them, or ſo eaſily to be caſhiered. But certainly I know none of the Ancients of that Sect have explained their meaning in that manner. You may ſee in <hi>Hippocrates</hi> in the place before cited, ſome held all things were made of fire, others of water, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of earth, but none of the mixture of them all; though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance ſome later Writers, preſſed by many abſurdities which would otherwiſe have followed, have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed their meaning otherwiſe. <hi>vid. Magnen. prop.</hi> 28. <hi>&amp;c. lib. tertij.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Poſsibly it may be urged, that ſome of the inconveniences that follow upon this doctrin of Atoms will fall out likewiſe upon that of Elements; for who brought them together to make the compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum?</p>
               <p>The Anſwer to this is eaſie to thoſe that believe the Creation.
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:55561:86"/>
                  <hi>Plato</hi> could tell you the beginning of things could not be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by ſenſe or imagination. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in ſeveral places ſpeaks of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſomething that was Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; ſo that they had ſome dark knowledge of the providence and government of God, which <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocritus</hi> and <hi>Epicurus</hi> derided; though neceſsity ſometime made rather ſome of their followers then themſelves let fall words ſounding toward the conceſsion of a Deity.</p>
               <p>Another opinion, ſomewhat different from thoſe before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and the commonly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Ariſtotelian</hi> Principles, is that of Mr. <hi>Des Cartes,</hi> a perſon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly of as ſublime a wit and deep reach as any that hath gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him; he finding that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Democritus</hi> and <hi>Epicurus</hi> was ſubject to great difficulties, which required bodies that had both figure and extenſion, not onely to be indiviſible, but alſo
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:55561:87"/>to move <hi>in vacuo,</hi> both which qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities he held abſurd and impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: and therefore endeavours, <hi>Princip. Phil. pars.</hi> 2. to prove there is no difference between <hi>ſpatium extenſum &amp; corpus,</hi> and that a <hi>ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium imaginarium immenſum</hi> fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied by ſome before the Creation, was impoſsible, becauſe no ſuch ſpace could be without a body to fill it, the nature of <hi>Body</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in extenſion, which in truth is no more then what <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> had ſaid long before, that there could be no <hi>ſpatium vacuum,</hi> becauſe there could be no terms of it. But from this <hi>ſuppoſitum</hi> Mr. <hi>Des Cartes</hi> concludes, and <hi>Regius</hi> his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that the matter of the whole Creation muſt needs be one and the ſame, both of bodies Celeſtial and Terreſtrial, becauſe the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>Matter</hi> or Body ſimply and univerſally conſidered, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting onely in extenſion, that being always the ſame, the matter
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:55561:87"/>muſt be ſo alſo. This you may ſee laid down by Mr. <hi>Des Cartes, Prin. Phil. p.</hi> 2. <hi>ſect.</hi> 22. <hi>Regii Philo. na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. p.</hi> 6. And having farther ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained local motion and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thereof, he comes in the third part of his <hi>Princ. Philoſ.</hi> to handle the Elements or moſt ſimple parts, out of which he conceives this <hi>Mundus aſpectibilis</hi> might have been framed; and this he lays down, not as a truth, but as an hypotheſis, from which all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances may be ſolved: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great Philoſopher, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all a Chriſtian, he tells you, that 'tis not to be doubted but that God at firſt created all things in their perfection by his infinite power, not out of Seeds or Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Yet for our better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the manner of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we may well conſider how all things might have been made by God, though that they were by him ſo made we know to he
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:55561:88"/>falſe. <hi>v. Phil. p. tent. ſect.</hi> 45. For the better explication of this, he ſuppoſeth, that after all that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of which the world conſiſts was made, it pleaſed God to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide it into magnitudes near equal to one another, endowed every one of them with that ſwiftneſs they now retain and keep, and that every one of theſe particles move in near a circular motion about its own centre, ſeperated and divided each of them one from the other. Theſe particles he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives to be of different irregular figures; that by their violent motion, hitting one againſt the other by Attrition, they did wear off a very thin duſt, which by reaſon of its extraordinary thinneſs and lightneſs he makes to be the firſt Element, and the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the third Heaven, which by reaſon of its infinite ſubtiltie was capable to inſinuate it ſelf, and fill up all vacuities in other bodies;
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:55561:88"/>and out of which firſt light, and after by a congregation of more of that matter the Sun was made. In the next place he ſuppoſeth, that by the attrition of theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles a ſecond ſort of matter was made, not ſo ſubtil as the firſt, out of this the Stars and Planets mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in their ſeveral Vortexes were framed. By this time theſe irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular figures by continual attriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wearing off the angles of one another, at laſt grew round, and what was worn off thicker and groſſer, out of this thickeſt part the Earth &amp; the things contained, he thinks to have been made and compoſed. So that the matter of all things is ſtill the ſame, differing onely in denſitie and raritie. This I take to be ſhortly the ſenſe of this Author, and by which as the moſt ſimple he conceives the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of nature may be ſolved, ſo that though things were not, yet it might have pleaſed God to have
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:55561:89"/>made them ſo. I think him thus far in the right, that he makes the <hi>Maximum diviſibile</hi> to be the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria prima,</hi> and divides that into particles, which in my judgment is more reaſonable, then to make Atoms concurre of themſelves by a volitation <hi>in vacuo,</hi> becauſe it is more agreeable to reaſon, that God made all things as they now are at firſt, and that their diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition by days, firſt, ſecond, &amp;c. was not that there were days with God, but to teach us the order of the Creation, and that there ſhould be days and times with us: and this ſeems to be the opinion of <hi>Du Hamel pag.</hi> 69. <hi>de conſenſ. vet. &amp; nov. Philoſ.</hi> and quotes St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> to back it. This Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis of this great Philoſopher ſeems to me to be ſubject to many im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probabilities: for why doth he make three Elements? if the matter be the ſame there is but one. Wheat and Flower is the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:55561:89"/>though the one be finer then the other. But if it be ſaid he underſtands denſitie in one ſubject, and rareneſs in another, which makes a difference in the things themſelves as to their effects, the more rare entring into the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Light, the Sun and Stars; the more thick and denſe to the making more dark &amp; opacous bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, why doth he not then make as many Elements as there are diverſities of denſitie and rareneſs?</p>
               <p>Secondly, I cannot conceive how there can be any motion in thoſe particles, out of which theſe Elements are made. For firſt, it is admitted that the great <hi>Expanſum</hi> hath extenſion, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is filled with ſome body or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which muſt then of neceſsity be contiguous one to the other, and conſequently no poſsibility of motion, except what is common to all the parts together, like a bladder filled with air. For either
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:55561:90"/>you muſt ſay, that the ſeveral faces of theſe particles meet together, which muſt hinder the motion or abraſion of one another, or elſe the angles of ſome muſt meet and touch the plains of others, then they will not <hi>complere locum ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> ſo that there muſt be an empty ſpace not filled with any thing, ſince that thin ſubtil mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that ſhould fill up all theſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuities is not in nature, till it be firſt made by abraſion. Thirdly, I ſee not Mr. <hi>Des Cartes</hi> make any contrarietie in theſe Elements, and ſo the ſame inconveniences will follow that did from the other opinions, to wit, that there ſhould be no paſsion, death, or alteration of bodies. For if theſe three Elements be made one out of the other, they muſt needs be homogeneous without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarietie, and ſo ſubject to no cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. To ſay that it may come from ſome diſturbance in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:55561:90"/>of that very ſubtile etherial matter which fills up the void ſpaces or pores in all bodies, is very hard to conceive. For firſt, admit that ſuch a diſturbance in the motion of that matter might cauſe an alteration or corruption, what extraneous matter ſhould cauſe that diſturbance I ſee not, nature of her ſelf never tending to her own deſtruction. Beſides, from hence it muſt follow, that corruption and alteration of all bodies comes from a cauſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, and not from any thing that enters into the texture of the body, or any indiſpoſition of the parts thereof. Laſtly, to ſay that thoſe little particles that go to the texture of any body do of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves diſunite, doth not avoid the precedent inconvenience, for it may be asked why they diſunite, or what made them come together to ſeperate? Neither can that be ſuppoſed of which no cauſe can be
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:55561:91"/>given. <hi>vid. Magnen. p.</hi> 302.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, I ſee little difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this opinion and that of <hi>Democritus,</hi> ſince they both agree there was an infinitie of ſmall parts, from the conjunction of which all greater bodies were made; in this they differ: one ſaith, they are ſolid, compact and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible; the other, that they are indefinite though not infinite, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible though not divided. One makes the little Atoms, firſt made by nature, and that by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe the great Machine of the world was made; the other ſaith, the great Expanſion was by God firſt created, &amp; that the ornaments and elements thereof were taken out of the great maſs by diviſion, and ſeparation of the parts of it.</p>
               <p>I come now to examine the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of our late Chymiſts touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beginning or elements of mixt bodies, and I ſhall as ſhortly as I can not onely ſhew their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:55561:91"/>but withall ſhew what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viation they have made from thoſe ancient Hermetick Philoſophers, from whom they at firſt deduced their notions. Theſe late Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers by fire, as they ſtyle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, finding that the ancient Hermetick Philoſophers made of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mention of <hi>Sulphure</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> in their writings, to which others added <hi>Salt;</hi> and farther finding them to make frequent mentions of Sublimation, Calci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Ablution, Circulation, Digeſtion, Reverberation, Fixa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the like; and alſo of the different Veſſels and Furnaces to be uſed in their Philoſophical works, adhering to the Letter, but deviating from the ſenſe, not conſidering the ſimple and eaſie waies of nature in the production of things, though ever inculcated to them in the ancient Writers, preſently fell to the invention of ſeveral Furnaces proper for thoſe
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:55561:92"/>ſeveral works as themſelves, not the true Philoſophers, underſtood them, who do not ſtick ſometime to tell you, that by Sublimation, Calcination, Circulation, Fixa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the like, they underſtand things quite different from what our vulgar Chymiſts mean; nay, that theſe ſeveral Operations are performed in one and the ſame Furnace, nay, in one and the ſame Veſſel, Nature being the true Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, who of it ſelf excites the central and natural Fire that lies hid in the prepared Matter, by the help of an artificial one in its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, adminiſtred by the hand of the Artiſt. So that Sublimation, Circulation, Digeſtion, Calcina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Fixation are but different ſteps in the ſame work. But this either not ſuiting with the humour or pride of later Wits, who thought nothing very good that was not attained by great labour, fell to inventing of ſeveral Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:55561:92"/>proper for theſe ſeveral works; thence came your <hi>Furnus Sublimatorius, Calcinatorius, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verberatorius, Circulatorius, Dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtivus,</hi> and as many more, as every man according to his ſeveral fancy pleaſed to think of. Next, finding that out of ſeveral things, both Mineral and Vegetable, by divers preparations and different admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations of Fire, they were able to produce different ſorts of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, ſome inſpid, ſome quick and piercing, ſome acid and ſharp, ſome viſcous, Unctuous and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamable, ſome ſaline, ſome fixed, have attributed to theſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ſeveral names, <hi>viz.</hi> to the watery inſipid part, phlegm; to the ſpiritual or piercing, Mercury; to the unctuous, Sulphur; the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line, Salt; the fixed, Earth; and make theſe to be the five Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or Elements of natural bodies. So Mr. <hi>Le Febvre,</hi> whoſe words are quoted by our Author, <hi>pag.</hi>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:55561:93"/>270. underſtanding Principles and Elements to be the ſame thing. So Mr. <hi>de Clave, cap.</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 40. tells you, they find onely five ſimple bodies in their laſt reſolution, and thinks them ridiculous who make any difference between <hi>Principia</hi> and <hi>Elementa.</hi> So that theſe five Principles muſt by them, at leaſt by our <hi>M. N.</hi> be held up <hi>excluſive</hi> to thoſe four of Fire, Air, Water and Earth, the notion of which muſt be look'd upon as frigid and vain, and theſe five lookt upon as the moſt ſimple Subſtances. In this Diſceptation it will not be unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy our obſervation, that theſe perſons having deduced their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Salt, Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> out of the Writings of the ancient Hermetick Philoſophers, ought not in reaſon to be believed far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they agree with their ancient Maſters, not where they differ from and fight againſt them: now 'tis very clear out of all their
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:55561:93"/>Writings, that by <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> they underſtood very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſomething latent in the <hi>Materia magiſterii,</hi> which matter they all held to be compounded of the four Elements, by the circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof in the <hi>Rota Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phica,</hi> the <hi>Magiſterium</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, when they then called <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur fixum, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſale ſolvens,</hi> nay ſometime <hi>Mercurius Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorum;</hi> not but that there was in it before it came to this heighth both <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latil part of the matter they called <hi>Mercury,</hi> ſometime the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, crude and undigeſted, without any previous preparation, was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Mercury,</hi> and this on purpoſe that they might conceal their Art from ſuch as they held unworthy to know it. The <hi>nexus utriuſque,</hi> to wit, of <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> they called <hi>Salt,</hi> which by many Philoſophers is left out, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in the Philoſophical work ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:55561:94"/>not, but as a <hi>vehiculum</hi> to ſet the other two at work, that ſo <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perius haberet naturam inferioris, &amp; inferius naturam ſuperioris.</hi> But there is nothing more clear from all their Writings, that they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the four Elements of Fire, Air, Water and Earth; this is very plain by <hi>Raimund Lully</hi> in <hi>codicillo cap.</hi> 33, 34, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> among the later Writers, <hi>Sendivogius</hi> throughout his Book. <hi>In tract. de Sulph.</hi> he hath theſe words, <hi>Sunt autem principia rerum, praeſertim metallorum, ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum antiquos Philoſophos due, Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur &amp; Mercurius; ſecundum Neote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricos vere tria, Sal, Sulphur, &amp; Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius. Origo autem horum princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piorum ſunt quatuor Elementa. Sciunt ergo ſtudio ſi hujus ſcientiae quatuor eſſe elementa, &amp;c.</hi> And in another place of the ſame Author, <hi>Duplex eſt materia metallorum</hi> (note, he ſaith not <hi>rerum omnium,</hi> but <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallorum) proxima, remota: proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma eſt Sulphur &amp; Mercurius, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mota
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:55561:94"/>ſunt quatuor Elementa, &amp;c.</hi> By which it is manifeſt theſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Philoſophers did not intend that theſe <hi>Principia</hi> of <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> ſhould juſtle out the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the four Elements, but held that of <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> diſtinct from them, and in the ſame Treatiſe handles the natures of them all diſtinctly and apart. The Author of that little Tractate cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Phyſica reſtituta, Can.</hi> 58. tells you, That all mixt bodies are made of two Elements, which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Earth and Water, in the which the other of Air and Fire are virtually included. In <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an. Hermet. Philoſoph. Can.</hi> 76. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e tells you, That the other Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are circulated in the form of Water. He tells you of <hi>Ignis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aturae in mixtis,</hi> and a <hi>Humor ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>calis,</hi> which are both immortal and inſeparable from any ſubject: explains his meaning by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of glaſs made out of aſhes,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:55561:95"/>which could not be made fluxile except there were in thoſe aſhes a radical moiſture; ſo of Salts. In ſumme, I know not one of them but admit, that in all bodies there is ſomething anſwerable to the four Elements of Fire, Air, Water and Earth, which we feel and handle, and by the mixture of which they are all, or at leaſt ſome of them, compoſed. <hi>[For by the way I would not be underſtood to ſay, that neceſſarily every body whatſoever muſt be compoſed of all the four Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for a mixture may be made, and ſome body, for ought I know, framed out of the conjunction of two or three of them; and 'tis enough for the ſupport of that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that there are four, to deduc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rationally that any one body is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of them.]</hi> By what hath been already ſaid it is evident, that the ancient Philoſophers did conceive and hold, that their <hi>Sulphur</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> is ſomething that lies hid
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:55561:95"/>in the heart of that matter which is compounded of the four Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. See <hi>Phyſ. reſtitut. Can.</hi> 224. That Sulphur anſwers to the <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum innatum,</hi> which is the ſpiritual fire, and <hi>Mercury</hi> to the <hi>humidum radicale.</hi> So that by thoſe names ſometimes they underſtand what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n mixt bodies hath ſome analogy with the Elements of Fire, Air and Water; for under <hi>humidum ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicale</hi> both Air and Water, in their ſenſe, are comprehended. At other times by Sulphur they underſtand the fixed matter, after the circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Elements through eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y degree of their Zodiack, and by <hi>Mercury</hi> the volatil part, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auſes that circulation to be made <hi>informa aquae,</hi> and <hi>in ventre aëris,</hi> till at laſt all ends <hi>in rupem illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tam,</hi> as they are pleaſed to phraſe it, which of it ſelf is a powerful remedy for all diſeaſes, and hath an ingreſs to the ſolution of all imperfect Metalls, and, as
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:55561:96"/>they ſay, after ſome ſuccedaneous preparations and repetition of the ſame work, will cauſe a tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of them. But they never underſtood that any of theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples ſhould deſtroy and put out of doors the four Elements, which themſelves always maintained. Some of the Chymiſts, I confeſs, as Monſieur <hi>de Clave</hi> and others, have denied an Elementary Fire, not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing between the material Fire we ſee in its effects, and that central we ſee not. So by their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious operations of the ancient Philoſophers, they have corrupted their ſenſe, and merited what <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divogius</hi> ſaith of them, <hi>Si hodie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viviſceret ipſe Philoſophorum pater Hermes, &amp; ſubtilis ingenii Geber, cum profundiſſimo Raimundo Lullio, non pro Philoſophis, ſed potius pro diſcipulis à noſtris Chemiſtis habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur. Neſcirent tot hodie uſitatas diſtillationes, tot circulationes, tot calcinationes, &amp; tot alia innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilia
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:55561:96"/>artiſtarum opera, quae hujus ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi homines ex illorum ſcriptis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venerunt &amp; excogitarunt.</hi> That is to ſay, If thoſe ancient and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Philoſophers, <hi>Hermes, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> and <hi>Lullius</hi> were alive, they would rather be accounted Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples then Philoſophers, who would not underſtand the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe many Diſtillations, Circulations, Calcinations, and innumerable other laborious ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations found by theſe Artiſts out of their Writings, contrary to the meaning of them. What reaſon therefore have we to believe, that theſe men have by their fiery and deſtructive trials found out the Principles or Elements from which mixt bodies have their compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when they have ſo much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken the ſenſe of thoſe Authors from whom they firſt took their names and notions of <hi>Sulphur, Salt</hi> and <hi>Mercury?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall onely touch at many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:55561:97"/>deductions, which in my judgment will follow out of this Doctrine. <hi>Firſt, Entia non ſunt multiplicanda niſi propter ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitatem.</hi> So that all thoſe parts in which humidity is prevalent, may be well comprehended under the Element of Water; ſuch are inſipid Phlegm, perhaps Spirit and Oyl, except you had rather reckon them of the Element of Fire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their inflammability. The drier parts under that of Earth, in which Air and Fire are included, which two likewiſe inſinuate themſelves into all other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded bodies, for I believe Air is in the moſt rectifi'd Spirit, and natural heat in all water whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, which cauſes firſt a fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and then a corruption. The different ſavours and viſcoſity may well be believed to proceed from the different wombs of the Earth, in which the elemental mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or matter produceth various
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:55561:97"/>off-ſprings; to wit, of Metalls, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſites, Stones, Plants, and the like, endued with thoſe ſeveral qualities and taſtes we find in them, participating in their nature of that part of the Earth whence they had their beginnings. Beſide, if this opinion ſhould be admitted, we muſt fancie as many Sulphurs as there are different ſorts of Oyls produced out of any body; ſo of the reſt. Neither do I ſee what more reaſon they have to ſay, that all Oyls, Phlegms and Spirits, though very different in their taſtes and effects, are the ſame Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Sulphur, Water and Mercury; they, I ſay, are all comprehended under that one of Water, in regard humidity is in them all moſt prevalent. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> in this reſolutory way of theirs, many bodies afford a vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til Salt that aſcends with the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be reſolved, and is different in effects, and not very like in taſte
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:55561:98"/>to that which is fixed and lies hid in the earthy part of the matter, till by calcination of it into aſhes any convenient <hi>Menſtruum</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes impregned with it, and that by evaporation of the <hi>Menſtruum</hi> taken out. I ſee not why theſe may not be called different Elements as well as Phlegm and Spirit, the one called <hi>Water,</hi> the other <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury;</hi> then in ſtead of five we have ſix Elements. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> in many of thoſe bodies which will be diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, all theſe different Elements will not, I think, be drawn, as out of your Reſins, out of which (<hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebintine</hi> for the purpoſe) I have never ſeen any fixed Salt made; <hi>Faber</hi> tells us of a volatil Salt to be taken out of it. From hence it will follow, that all bodies are not compounded of the ſame number of Elements. The like may be ſaid of your <hi>Pinguedines</hi> and many Gums. I think no body will deny that our ordinary Water, or, if
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:55561:98"/>you pleaſe, <hi>May</hi> dew is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, yet will it be found, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, paſt the cunning of theſe Artiſts to draw from it either a burning Spirit or inflameable Oyl. I am not ignorant that <hi>Faber</hi> ſpeaks of a ſharp burning Spirit, drawn, as he ſaith, out of Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, he counts it for a <hi>Panacea,</hi> and it may, I believe, be ſo judged, when 'tis attained without ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtication. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> what ſhall we ſay to the Tincture taken ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times out of the crude matter, both Vegetable and Mineral, which ſhall notwithſtanding, after they are bereaved of their Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, yield the ſame Salts, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, Phlegms and Oyls they did whilſt they were full of it? Under what Claſsis ſhall we put theſe Tinctures? why may we not rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon them another Element? &amp; then we have gotten ſeven, <hi>viz.</hi> Earth, Phlegm, volatil Salt, fixed Salt, Spirit, Oyl and Tincture. If you
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:55561:99"/>ſay that Tincture is but a ſubtil part of that body out of which 'twas drawn, I admit it, but ſtill 'tis a part of that body endued with a colour taken out of the whole, and of which the whole by that means is bereaved. Nay, what will he ſay to him that ſhall ſhew him a ſubſtance drawn out of the aſhes of an ordinary Vegetable, after their Salt is taken away, which evidently ſhews that thoſe very aſhes which, according to this Doctrin, ſhould be the pure Element of Earth, are ſtill a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound body? Farther, what will he ſay to the Quinteſſences drawn by Chymiſts, what to the <hi>Prima entia</hi> of many ſubſtances both Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getable and Mineral, ſpoken of by <hi>Paracelſus</hi> in the end of his Tractate <hi>De Renovatione &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauratione?</hi> what are theſe? and why may not theſe be called <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipia</hi> as well as any of thoſe named by our Author? So are we not
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:55561:99"/>certain at laſt how many <hi>Principia</hi> we may come to. <hi>Paracelſus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is more modeſt, for he tells you <hi>in tractatu de rebus naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, cap.</hi> 4. <hi>De ſale &amp; ſub ſale con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentis. Conſtat homo ex tribus, Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phure, Mercurio, Sale. Ex his etiam conſtat quiequid ubivis eſt, &amp; nec paucioribus nec pluribus.</hi> And in another place tells you, <hi>de tribus principiis, cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Id quod ardet Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur eſt, quod effumat eſt Mercurius, qui cinis relinquitur Sal eſt.</hi> By which words 'tis clear, that under Aſhes he comprehends our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Earth and Salt, under Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur whatſoever is inflammable; ſo that our Author's Oyl and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are comprehended under the name of Sulphur, and under that of Mercury the parts of any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that will aſcend in a ſmoke or vapour; by which two things are very manifeſt. Firſt, that <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus</hi> here ſpake in the ſenſe of other ancient Philoſophers, and
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:55561:100"/>did not take theſe ſubſtances as things to ſhoulder out the four Elements, which in another Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate he particularly defends, and ſhews how they are in the body under the form of the four hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours; ſo that it ſeems neither the Doctrine of the Elements nor of the four Humours were look'd upon as fancies by <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus.</hi> Secondly, That theſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances were look'd upon by him as compounds, and ſo not as the Elements and moſt ſimple parts of the mixt body, contrary to what Mr. <hi>De Clave</hi>'s and our Author, out of <hi>Le Febvre,</hi> have delivered, for in them all will <hi>Mercury</hi> be found, for they will all give a ſmoke if they be ſet upon the fire and made boil, except the drie Aſhes diveſted of its Salt. Of the ſame opinion is Dr. <hi>Willis,</hi> who tells you, he doth indeed find thoſe five ſubſtances in bodies, but doth not deliver them as moſt
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:55561:100"/>ſimple beings altogether uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, but onely as ſuch ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible parts, by the motion, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination, inequality or ſeparation whereof bodies are augmented or periſh, and this to the end that men may, in his judgment, better underſtand by the view of theſe more groſs parts how Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made, then by the more abſtracted notion of the four Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which never in their purity come under the ſenſes. In all this there is no abſurdity, and let him in God's name enjoy his opinion that conceives he can this way bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter explain the appearances of Nature. But the underſtanding of theſe ſubſtances in this ſenſe can be no part of our <hi>M. N.</hi>'s meaning, who makes uſe of them to thruſt out of doors the frigid notion of the four Elements, with the fancy of Humours and Qualities; tells you theſe are the Principles or Elements of natural bodies, in
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:55561:101"/>which after their reduction, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing heterogeneous can be found; whereas the ancient Philoſophers as well as <hi>Paracelſus</hi> and Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> do admit theſe which he calls Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be ſtill compounded bodies, and do all, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, allow both of Qualities, Humours and four Elements, as I have ſhewed before, and is yet more cleared, when we conſider that in the driving off of the Oils from many acid bodies, Vitriol for the purpoſe, part of the ſubſtance of the Mineral it ſelf comes over with the Oil, which in time will of it ſelf precipitate in the air in the form of that body was drawn off, and, to my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in all reſpects the ſame, and ſo not the volatile Salt which perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture others might, and my ſelf did at firſt ſuppoſe, till upon trial I was ſatisfi'd otherwiſe. I have by me at this preſent a Balſame of Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, which I prepared above
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:55561:101"/>fifteen years ſince, which ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains as high a tincture to outward appearance as it had at firſt, and yet hath let fall ſome of my Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur to the bottom, which could not come thither, had it not in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance firſt aſcended into the <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruum,</hi> for whether it riſe three inches or ten is not material: but this is certain, it remained all in the form of a liquor for many years. I might adde, that many of theſe ſubſtances will in time cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and ſtink, others nouriſh, which cannot well be conceived from what is ſimple, and hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it heterogeneous. Thus I have done with the examination of the ſeveral opinions, and come now to the laſt <hi>Ariſtotelian</hi> way of the compoſition of mixt bodies out of the four Elements, in which we have, after all this clamour of our <hi>M. N.</hi> and thoſe of his party, this advantage, that two of them are granted to our hand, <hi>viz. Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:55561:102"/>and <hi>Earth;</hi> as for the other two, the parties are divided, ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying an elementary fire, others admitting fire and denying Air; perhaps their miſtake may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from not being able to form to themſelves any Idea of Fire and Air, except what they ſee and feel in their effects; whereas undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly the elementary Earth and Water are as different in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from that Earth and Water we ſee, as the Fire and Air in their elements are different from thoſe we ſee and feel. But the Ancients, with <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and his followers, finding by experience that there were four contrary qualities, to wit, Heat, Coldneſs, Drought, Moiſture, and that theſe being accidents muſt needs inhere in ſome ſubject, did from hence ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally enough deduce, that that ſubject in which heat was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any mixture, might be well called the element of Fire, and ſo
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:55561:102"/>of the reſt. Finding, ſecondly, that moſt bodies, as well animate as other, were endued with a certain temperament, that is to ſay, ſome in which heat prevailed, yet ſo alloied with coldneſs, that the heat did not utterly conſume and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the <hi>compoſitum;</hi> others in which Drought was moſt intenſe, yet attempered in ſome meaſure with moiſture, deduced, that this temperament could not well be introduced in nature, without a mixture of thoſe qualities which reſided purely in their elements; hence came firſt the notion of the four Elements, found out prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily by the conſideration of the four qualities, the mixture of the Elements in the compoſition of bodies, by the temperament of them; ſo that the qualities and temperament, the one introduced the Elements, the other the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of them, in which they were careful to diſtinguiſh between ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:55561:103"/>confuſion and mixture; appoſition, where two different things were put together, ſo as again they might be ſeperated, as, for the purpoſe, different ſeeds or grains. Confuſion, where diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things were put together, which could not be ſeparated, yet introduced not a new form, ſuch is the putting of wine and water together, which retains ſtill the ſame form it had of liquor. Laſtly, Mixture properly ſo called, in which, by moſt Authors, theſe four conditions are required. Firſt, that the <hi>Miſcibilia</hi> muſt be endued with contrary qualities, that they may mutually act and ſuffer one from the other, for otherwiſe they would remain in the ſame ſtate without any mixtion at all. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, there muſt be a certain proportion both in quantity and quality, otherwiſe one would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the other, and there could be no temperament. Now this
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:55561:103"/>proportion and contrariety in the Miſcibles, if it be of equality, produceth a temperament <hi>ad Pondus,</hi> which ſo long as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in any body, that (as it ſeems to me) cannot receive any change or alteration. But where there is not that equality both in quantity and quality, but that one prevails over the other in ſome meaſure, yet not ſo to deſtroy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily the <hi>Compoſitum,</hi> this is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Temperament <hi>ad Juſtitiam,</hi> by which the <hi>Compoſitum</hi> may be preſerved for many years in a good eſtate, yet at laſt, from the conſtant fight of theſe contrary qualities, alteration, death and corruption at laſt let in. Thirdly, the Elements muſt be ſo put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that every part of the <hi>Compoſitum</hi> muſt retain them all four. And, laſtly, that they muſt remain formally <hi>in Mixto.</hi> I know this laſt is controverted by ſome Writers, yet I believe will, upon
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:55561:104"/>examination, be found a truth, but the diſputation thereof is not for this place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Avicenna, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>d.</hi> 2. proves the Elements from the neceſſary things that muſt concur to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of every natural body; he tells you, no generation can be without a fixion of the matter and extenſion, a dilution and permea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the parts, a ſubtiliation and mixture with motion: he tells you, fixion comes from the Earth, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion and dilution from the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, permeation and ſubtiliation from the Air, the motion of the mixed from the Fire; and then concludes, that ſince thoſe things are neceſſary to all generations, and are ſupplied by thoſe four Elements, thoſe Elements muſt needs have exiſtence to ſupply that office. This argumentation from this learned <hi>Arabian,</hi> will, upon good conſideration, be found to have more weight then at firſt
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:55561:104"/>ſight doth perhaps appear. Of this I am ſure, that this, with thoſe before drawn from the combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the four qualities amongſt many others, have ſo far prevailed with the world, that they have, I think, for nigh, if not full 2000 years, been thought reaſonable, and therefore not ſo eaſily to be exploded, and thought dry and jejune notions, as our <hi>M. N.</hi> would have them. Let every man, however, for me, ſafely enjoy his own opinion, and the learned judge which carries moſt weight of reaſon.</p>
               <p>I ſhould now come to a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular examination of the eighth and ninth Chapters of his book, which are very long, but contain in them nothing, or little more then a repetition of what hath been ſeveral times inculcated in other parts of his Book, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready taken notice of. What he
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:55561:105"/>ſpeaks touching Digeſtion, Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, and the miſtake of the Schools in the notion of Diſeaſes, whether a diſeaſe be onely a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper in the exceſs of qualities, as the <hi>Galeniſts,</hi> or a real ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial thing inherent in the <hi>Archeus,</hi> as <hi>Helmont,</hi> may admit of an end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs diſpute; but he ſhould do well to explain what they mean by <hi>Archeus,</hi> and how a diſeaſe can be inherent in it, or how any Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine can work upon a Spirit and incorporeal thing, or diſeaſe cured, except it can be done by means of the qualities in corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting their exceſs. I am ſure none of them have hitherto delivered us any ſuch Medicine or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and till then, for ought I ſee, we muſt be content with our old ones. No more to the purpoſe is what he ſaith in the ſame Chapter touching the diſtribution of the <hi>Chyle,</hi> in which the new diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries have not at all altered the
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:55561:105"/>old method, which ſtands firm upon its ancient baſe of long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and practiſe. Neither doth he or any other make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that Chymical preparations, which he onely contends for, do otherwiſe operate then the other <hi>Galenick</hi> ones do, <hi>viz.</hi> by Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, Vomit, Sweat, Urine, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion or Tranſpiration, which effect they had long before the new diſcoveries in Anatomy were at all made known to the world: and therefore from that Topick, no caſting off the old Medicines, and erecting a new method can be evinced. What is new in his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry long ninth and laſt Chapter, (except his carping at <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> who is vindicated enough in Dr. <hi>Sprackling</hi>) is the Doctrin of Critical days, Urines and Pulſes. I ſhall ſpeak very ſhortly to them all.</p>
               <p>As for the hypercritical Doctrin of Critical Days, that he derides,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:55561:106"/>and calls it as childiſh a conceit, &amp;c. tells you 'tis like children's game called <hi>Even and Odd,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, forſooth, the indicatory days fall upon every fourth, the decretory or critical upon every ſeventh day, ſaith, this doctrin is uſeful for two ends; firſt, to cloak the ignorance of Practiſers; and, ſecondly, to hide the inſufficiency of the Art: and yet withal is forced to admit, that this <hi>ſhameful conceit,</hi> as he terms it, hath been received in the world for 2000 years, and ſo indeed hath it ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally been, and the truth of their aſſertion grounded upon conſtant experience. So that it muſt be either conceded that there is truth in the thing, or that the aſſertors have been all igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and have uſed this as a cloak to hide that and the inſufficiency of their Art. 'Tis ſtrange that for 2000 years there hath been no learned Phyſician, but ſuch as have
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:55561:106"/>obtruded things falſe and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and not onely ſo, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with their pens their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and given reaſons for it, which had it been uſed as a cloak to ignorance, they needed not have done. But now in this learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Age of ours, <hi>M. N.</hi> is ſprung up to carp at all the Ancients, and yet offers nothing of his own ſo good as what we have received from them. But he vouchſafes at laſt, <hi>page</hi> 313. for the information <hi>of his Countrymen, to deſcend to a view of the odde conceits of the even and odd gameſters about criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal days.</hi> Is pleaſed moreover to let us know that in his judgment <hi>Hippocrates</hi> was wiſer then his followers, and that <hi>Avicenna</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> in that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, becauſe he contented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf onely with experience. Pray, Sir, if he delivered you nothing but obſervation, why do you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride him? Is a man to be ſcorned
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:55561:107"/>becauſe <hi>M. N.</hi> doth not believe what he ſaith? He that ſhall read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him <hi>de Principiis,</hi> ſhall find many handſom obſervations of the Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenary number, as well in the conception, growth and dentition of children, as alſo of the ſame Number in acute ſickneſſes: And in the end of his Book, <hi>de Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus,</hi> tells you, that Fevers are judged the fourth, the ſeventh, the eleventh, the fourteenth, &amp;c. This that he hath thus delivered hath paſſed current ever ſince, onely upon the truth of his and the concurrent obſervations of others. But he tells you 'tis lawful to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject <hi>experience againſt experience; that in our days things fall out as well upon other days as thoſe he calls Critical.</hi> I am glad yet he allows that ſuch changes fall out upon thoſe days <hi>Hippocrates</hi> called Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical. Who ever ſaid they never fell out upon other? I am ſure <hi>Hippocrates</hi> doth not; nay, he tells
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:55561:107"/>you, that thoſe changes will fall out commonly, though no Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick at all be given. He doth not ſay, the Medicine rightly and duly or unduly adminiſtred, may not either haſten or retard the <hi>Criſis,</hi> which may alſo happen from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other cauſes. From the great leader <hi>hippocrates</hi> he comes to his followers, the embracers of the <hi>Pythagorean</hi> fancy of the myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous power of the number Seven, which, ſay they, may have effect upon men, though the cauſe be not known. I will not enter into that high ſpeculation, but remit him to the <hi>Jewiſh Cabaliſts,</hi> to <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> and his Ideas of later ſtanding, to <hi>Leo, Iſaurus, Brentius, Cornelius Agrippa, Trithemius, Gaffarel,</hi> and many others, thought in their times learned men, and yet did not think the myſtical doctrine of Numbers ſo vain and idle a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit as <hi>M. N.</hi> would have us think it. <hi>I, but</hi> Galen <hi>hath confuted that
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:55561:108"/>Doctrin well enough, but has lapſed into a worſe errour.</hi> 'Tis true, <hi>Galen</hi> hath ſpoke much againſt the fancy of the myſtery in Numbers, and with becoming gravity and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, but that he has lapſed into a worſe error, by attributing the cauſe of the <hi>Criſis</hi> in acute ſickneſs to the motion of the Moon, is more then <hi>M. N.</hi> will well prove. It cannot with any colour of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be denied, but that the Moon hath very great influence upon ſublunary bodies, this is evident enough from many Shell-fiſhes, Rabbets, and many other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, who ſome in their brain, ſome in other parts, receive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe or diminution in ſuch a Phaſis of the Moon. Your <hi>Lunatici, Epileptici,</hi> men bitten with mad dogs, have always their acceſſes with more vigour, either at the increaſe or full of the Moon; why therefore it ſhould have no power over the bodies of men, from
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:55561:108"/>whence judgment may be made, is paſt my underſtanding. Againſt it he urges, <hi>If it were ſo, then the ſquares and weeks of the Moon would always concur with the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternions and weeks of the diſeaſe, but this very rarely falls out.</hi> I am troubled to make ſenſe of theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> what he means by quaternion of the diſeaſe, if he mean the fourth day from the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubitus,</hi> as I think he doth, then he is much in the right, for the ſquare or week of the Moon never did, nor never can concur with the fourth day of the diſeaſe, unleſs the Moon could go above twenty degrees in a day: if he would have the quaternion of the diſeaſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the ſquare of the Moon, then his words muſt ſound thus, The ſquare and week of the Moon ſhould anſwer to the ſquare and week of the diſeaſe. But who ever heard of the ſquare of a diſeaſe? The truth is, the ſquare and week
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:55561:109"/>of the Moon is one and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thing, for in the ſeventh day from the <hi>decubitus,</hi> the Moon always goes 90 degrees, or thereabout, in her own Orb, and ſo hath a quartile aſpect with that degree of the Zodiack that was aſcendant at the time of the <hi>decubitus,</hi> which is ſometime called the ſquare of the Moon, becauſe it is the chord of 90 degrees, and conſequently the ſide of the greateſt ſquare can be inſcribed in that circle, and comprehends in its four angles the cuſps of the firſt, the fourth, the ſeventh and tenth Houſes. Now the Moon, the fourth day from the <hi>decubitus,</hi> comes to a ſextile of the aſcendant, which being an aſpect of amity, if the Moon be likewiſe well aſpected by the other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, is ſaid by Aſtrologers to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate a good event of that ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſo conſequently a good <hi>Criſis</hi> on the ſeventh day when ſhe comes to quartile, which may
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:55561:109"/>decree good or bad according to the nature of thoſe Planets that are then with the Moon, or aſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by her. So on the eleventh, when ſhe comes to a trine, the fourteenth to an oppoſition, and ſo of the reſt, till ſhe hath ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved her Circle, before which time acute ſickneſſes are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly judged. Not that theſe indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and decretal days do always juſt meet in that direct number of days to an hour, becauſe the Moon is ſometimes <hi>velox,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>tarda curſu;</hi> but he that is careful may gather much from them. Again, men are ſometime deceived in the time of the <hi>Criſis,</hi> becauſe they know not from what time preciſely to reckon the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubitus;</hi> but he that ſhall heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obſerve the firſt great muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in a ſickneſs, and accordingly look back from that time, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the <hi>decubitus,</hi> he will gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally find the mutations happen
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:55561:110"/>according to the rules and days before mentioned: I am ſure if it be otherwiſe, the Aſtrologers are much deceived. So is <hi>Argolus,</hi> who in his Book <hi>De diebus criticis,</hi> hath given many obſervations of the event of ſickneſſes, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned according to theſe grounds. So that for ought I ſee, the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of diſeaſes from the motion of the Moon and her aſpects is not ſo frivolous as <hi>M. N.</hi> would have it, nor perhaps ſo much to be attended as ſome others require it ſhould be; onely I would give our Author that advertiſement, not hereafter to gainſay thoſe opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that have had long footing in the world, without he were able to give demonſtrative reaſons againſt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paracelſus</hi> reckons the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of Aſtronomy as neceſſary to a Phyſician, therefore could be no enemy to critical days. The opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Fracaſtorius</hi> I let paſs, and
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:55561:110"/>ſhall now have done with the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of critical days, leaving <hi>Aſclepiades</hi> and <hi>Celſus</hi> to their opinions, without quarrelling with them, though they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next exception he takes is at <hi>Galen</hi>'s too ſcrupulous deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of the Pulſe, and reduceth its motion to a far leſſer number of varieties. He ſhall not have me his enemy in this matter, I agree with him, the varieties he enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates are enough, and more then are generally obſerved; yet how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever let us thank <hi>Galen</hi> for his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and if at any time we ſhould light upon any variety in the Pulſe not comprehended in this Writers ten varieties, let him remember <hi>Galen</hi> had taken notice of it before. <hi>Sennertus,</hi> and out of him <hi>Johnſtonus,</hi> is content with three varieties, <hi>viz. Aequalis, &amp; inequalis, velox tardus, validus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis:</hi> ſo that he may ſee that all
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:55561:111"/>the Dogmaticks were not ſo nice to inſiſt upon all the ſubtilties of <hi>Herophilus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching the judgment of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines, I ſhall refer him to <hi>Foreſtus</hi> and <hi>Fernelius,</hi> from both which Authors it will appear, that the Urine is not ſufficient in all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes to make a perfect judgment, though in many it is a great help, eſpecially thoſe ſickneſſes that are acute, as well as diſeaſes of the Reins, Kidneys, Bladder, Obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and ſome others. But our Author tells us, he is onely for rectification and improvement of the doctrine of Urins, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds out of Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> ways of reſolving them into thoſe he calls the Chymical Principles, that by this means the <hi>temperature may be rightly inveſtigated.</hi> I ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his or any man's diligence that ſhall contribute any thing to the improvement of our Art, where his own time and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:55561:111"/>will give him leave; let us onely be thus far wary, not to miſtake and call that an improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which perhaps is none, or not at all conducible to that great end of more ſpeedy and ſecure curing a diſeaſe; to which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I do not yet find any of our new and learned ſpeculations touching the motion of the Bloud, the carriage of the Chyle, the manner of ſanguification, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of Medicines into the veins, have proved hitherto very effectual. In the mean time I would not be thought to take from the due praiſe of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that have laboured herein, and candidly imparted their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations for the benefit of the Profeſsion, without upbraiding thoſe Authors to whom the world is beholding for much of that knowledge it now enjoys, by their communication of their labours to thoſe that came after them.</p>
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:55561:112"/>
               <p>His invectives againſt <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> which hold him many pages, I ſhall let paſs, till the vindication of them by Dr. <hi>Sprackling</hi> ſhall be anſwered by this undertaker.</p>
               <p>Touching bleeding in Scorbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick diſeaſes, Fevers, &amp;c. I ſhall be very ſhort, having had occaſion to ſpeak more fully to it in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of this Treatiſe; my mind not being to follow him in his unneceſſary repetitions of the ſame thing. <hi>Pag.</hi> 383. he gives us caution <hi>to be very wary of drawing bloud in our climate, in regard of the univerſal ſpreading of the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butical tincture.</hi> After that, gives you the judgment of <hi>Thonerus,</hi> againſt bleeding in Fevers in the Northern climates, confirms this by the different nature of the bloud of <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Germans,</hi> that in one 'tis ſafe, in the other dangerous; out of <hi>Zacutus Luſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus.</hi> Thus far he and I ſhall
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:55561:112"/>agree, that not onely in the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute and Fevers in Northern, but Southern climates alſo, caution is to be uſed in bleeding, as alſo in the uſe of all other Medicines. The want of this is what we blame in our <hi>M. N.</hi> and others of the ſame feather, who would make us believe they can cure all mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies with ſome one or two Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical preparations, which they uſe promiſcuouſly, without any caution or conſideration had of the temperature of the party, the prevalency of the peccant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, or preparation of the body to make it more fit for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of more potent remedies. As to bleeding in the Scorbute, I ſee not why it may not ſafely be adminiſtred, provided the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butick pollution be before well corrected, the ſtomach ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the chylification made good, ſo that a good and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome juice be carried (by what
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:55561:113"/>
                  <hi>ductus</hi> is not material) to the heart. Bleeding at this time may be properly made uſe of, for in regard the whole maſs of bloud is infected with that acid ſaline quality he ſpeaks of; I think it more rational to draw part of the infected bloud away, that the good chyle mingling with the reſt, may correct what remains; a part of its burthen being taken away, then to ſuffer the ſame Chyle, by a continual and daily ſupply to correct the whole. To <hi>Thonerus</hi> I ſhall onely ſay what a very learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Phyſician, yet alive, replied to me, when I told him that <hi>Ludo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicus Septelius</hi> diſallowed very much the uſe of <hi>Rhubarb</hi> in purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing choler, and asked his opinion. He bad me not give heed to the opinion of one man againſt the current of all practiſers; this is the eaſe with <hi>Thorenus,</hi> and ſome few others of his ſide. I am certain, if we believe report, that great Wit
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:55561:113"/>
                  <hi>Des Cartes</hi> died in <hi>Sweden</hi> of a Pluriſie, becauſe he refuſed to make uſe of that known remedy of letting bloud. Neither ſee I any reaſon why the ſtrong Wines, hot Spices and ſucculent Meats uſed in cold countries, may not as eaſily inflame the bloud as in hotter Climates, where the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal heat is much alloyed by their conſtant uſe of cooling Fruits, Sallets, much Water, and little uſe of Fleſh-meats in their diets, we ſee Fevers do ariſe, and are often cured by bleeding.</p>
               <p>Touching bleeding in malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Fevers, when ſafe, when otherwiſe, I have ſpoken alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, nor ſhall now trouble the Reader, no more then I ſhall to anſwer our Author's own obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, <hi>page</hi> 416. which muſt ſtand or fall upon the obſervers authority; ſo muſt that fancy of the difference of the <hi>Italian</hi> and <hi>German</hi> bloud. After this,
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:55561:114"/>
                  <hi>page</hi> 432, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he makes an inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating digreſsion to the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries,
<note place="margin">Pag. 419.</note> wiſhes for their eaſe, <hi>that the crude, fulſome, ill-conditioned Meſſes, and Mixtures, and Liquors may be thrown out of doors,</hi> and this out of a ſuppoſition that he hath overthrown <hi>the trifling no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of Elements, Qualities, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraments, Complexions, &amp;c. toward the confutation whereof he hath not made the leaſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, nor anſwered any reaſon alledged for them farther then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling their Aſſertors, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident avowing for undoubted truths the wild fancies of his own brain; but however, the Shops are to be reformed, and all ſet upon a new baſis of Chymical and experimental Phyſick, and this, forſooth, becauſe the <hi>Galeniſts</hi> ſeeing their own old remedies ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſufficient, fall themſelves on the Chymical practiſe, though they do it by ſtealth, (as Mr. <hi>Le
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:55561:114"/>Febvre</hi> ſaith) and the quainter practiſers <hi>become Semi-chymiſts, dividing their practiſe between the Laborator and the Shop.</hi> And in this they <hi>do well, and want but little of true converſion,</hi> ſeeing the onely thing remains to be done is the throwing aſide the old prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Methods, &amp;c. and 435. recites out of Mr. <hi>Le Febvre his great charity to them, and his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to advance the dignity of Pharmacy,</hi> viz. <hi>the Art of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary, that now lies bending to its ruine, &amp;c. Pag.</hi> 437. he tells you, that <hi>by theſe words of Mr.</hi> Le Febvre, <hi>the Apothecary Royal;</hi> the other Apothecaries are at a ſtand, inaſmuch as the ſtream of practiſe running towards this new way, <hi>and the pedantick Galeniſts and ſemi-chymiſts not knowing how to attempt a cure but by preſcribing the old ſtuff.</hi> The Apothecaries are bound to have it, leſt they loſe that ſort of practiſe. His ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:55561:115"/>therefore is, <hi>pag.</hi> 439. <hi>for the ſupport of ſo worthy a Society as the Apothecaries, that they ſhould be indulged to make uſe of their own Medicines at their own diſcretion among the Sick, ſeeing the prudent part of them underſtand the nature of them, and the old rode of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe belonging to them as well as (if not better then) the Galeniſts;</hi> and this to continue <hi>till the old Galenick formalities be laid aſleep or reformed, &amp;c.</hi> If the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries ſhall be miſled by this kind of Sophiſtry, I ſhould much won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in which he lays open his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign too evidently, which is not at all to benefit them, but himſelf and thoſe of his brotherhood, and cauſe the Apothecaries to mutiny both among themſelves and that body by which they have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to been ſupported. Why ſhould he otherwiſe ſuppoſe that the ſtream of practiſe runs his way; that the <hi>pedantick Galeniſts</hi> and
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:55561:115"/>
                  <hi>Semi-chymiſts,</hi> nay, the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries themſelves, were not able to prepare their own Chymical remedies, excluſive to all other, if the thing he ſuppoſeth were true, and that they found it ſo? What unknown preparation have they made publick? what new thing are we beholding to the Apothecary Roial for in all his courſe of Chymiſtry? have we not Books enough ſtuffed with Chymical preparations? have we not <hi>Libavius, Baſilius Valentinus, Quercetane, Faber, Beguin, Crollius, Hartman, Scroderus, Minſichius, Angelus Sala,</hi> and many others both <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Writers? What hath the Apothecary Roial which Dr. <hi>French</hi> hath not in the Engliſh Tongue, before him, or Tranſlations, for the ſubſtance of the preparation, out of ſome of the Books before mentioned? But that 'tis the nature of this ſort of Operators, if they make the leaſt
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:55561:116"/>alteration, (as for the purpoſe, from diſtilled Water to May-dew) to look upon the preparation with ſuch a ſlight alteration, as wholly their own, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning thanks to him from whom they ſtole it. Why then muſt the Apothecaries be indulged a liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of practiſe, till their old ſtock of <hi>Galenick</hi> remedies, and their Meſſes and Mixtures which they are forced to keep for that ſort of practiſe, are worn out? I tell you why, to the end that by that time this <hi>M. N.</hi> and thoſe of his party may have ſet up a Labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory, from which they pretend all preparations after their new model ſhould be made, and the Apothecaries furniſhed at eaſie rates from their ſtock: this is clearly their drift, as in another place is expreſſed by this Writer. But, pray, how have theſe men monopolized all Chymical Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the <hi>Semi-chymiſts, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantick
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:55561:116"/>Galeniſts</hi> and Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries may not be Maſters of that part of Learning as well as they? Away, away, <hi>M. N.</hi> with this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenuous dealing; if you are Maſter of any new piece of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in this kind, make the world partakers of it, and for my part I ſhall be one of the firſt ſhall give you your due praiſe; otherwiſe let me tell you, 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath a Gentleman, unworthy a Scholar, unbeſeeming a man, to affix unhandſom names and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches upon thoſe you know not, and perhaps ſuch as have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured more, and ſeen as much in ſuch as you call Chymical pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations as you have done, <hi>viz.</hi> in ſeveral ſorts of preparations of <hi>Vitriol, Salt, Antimony, Mercury, Sulphur, Salt-peter,</hi> and out of every of theſe made good and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate remedies, and ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully uſed them in many diſeaſes, yet never found that effect that it
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:55561:117"/>was fit to make uſe of them onely to the excluſion of all the reſt of the <hi>Materia Medica.</hi> As for the Apothecaries, I ſhall leave them to their own judgment, not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but the ancient method of Phyſick will be ſupported without any other aſsiſtance then its own worth. And to you, <hi>M. N.</hi> I wiſh more temper and conſiſtence of judgment, for though you ſtrike here at the old Method and Rules, yet in the cloſe of your Book, <hi>page</hi> 496. you ſeem to be more moderate, and will be content to allow ſome more latitude in the uſe of Simples and ſingle Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficks. I ſhould have look'd upon this as a little retractation of what went before, for how can the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of diſeaſes be changed, and a new method neceſſarily intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, if the old Simples and Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificks will yet in ſome caſes ſerve the turn? But the miſchief is, you are not long in this mood, for I
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:55561:117"/>find your hand ſubſcribed under an engagement entred into by ſome of your company, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the inſtituting an Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration of Profeſſors of Phyſick, <hi>Onely by Hermetick or Chymical Phyſick, and in thoſe their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to be aſſiſtant to one another, and never to relinquiſh that their engagement for any temporal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects whatſoever.</hi> To let paſs the danger of theſe kinds of engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and how the beſt, nay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps all Profeſsions, nay Trades, may be capable of improvement in the judgment of ſome raſh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers; and the manifeſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth in the ſuppoſition upon which all this is built, to wit, <hi>That after ſufficient experiment it is found moſt true, that Chymical Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines well prepared, and as well applied, are above all others the ſafeſt, pleaſanteſt and moſt effectual means, both for conſervation of health, and cure of all diſeaſes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</hi>
                  <pb n="210" facs="tcp:55561:118"/>I would ask <hi>M. N.</hi> how he can engage to improve the Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Phyſick <hi>Onely</hi> by Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick and Chymical Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, except he underſtand the uſe of them excluſive to all others, whether Simples or Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificks? What ever is Chymically made, or otherwiſe, may be called, according to its nature, an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, a Salt, a Spirit, an Oil, or what you will; but certainly 'tis not a Medicament but in its uſe and application: and I cannot believe <hi>M. N.</hi> did intend onely to know Chymical preparations, and not in like manner onely to make uſe of ſuch, and no other at leaſt at that time when he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed that <hi>Engagement.</hi> But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps between the publiſhing his Book and his ſubſcription he had changed his mind, or warily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that every Clyſter, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeme, or diſtilled Water from any Simple or Specifick, may be as
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:55561:118"/>well called a Chymical Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as their Salt, Oils or Spirits, which are all made by the Fire, ſome in a cloſe, ſome in an open one, and therefore the Preparers as deſervedly called <hi>Pyrotechniſts</hi> as any of theſe. If in this I have miſtaken his meaning, I ſhall be willing to ask his pardon, when he makes me underſtand it. But that the Reader may know where this Engagement is, he ſhall find it printed at the end of a Book called, <hi>The Poor man's Phyſician,</hi> put out <hi>By Thomas Odowde</hi> (as he calls himſelf) <hi>Eſquire, one of the Grooms of the Chamber to his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty, King</hi> CHARLES <hi>the Second.</hi> Now that at the ſame time you may know the jugling of theſe kind of dealers, and how likely this Eſquire is to make his Boy do ſuch ſtrange Cures, which it ſeems a ſworn Phyſician of the Kings could not, as appears by a Letter of his, <hi>page</hi> 75. of his book.
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:55561:119"/>Be pleaſed to underſtand, that by the omiſsion of three Letters he hath confounded one of the moſt honourable employments about the King, with one of the moſt inferiour, I think, of any above ſtairs; for had he called himſelf Groom of the <hi>Bed</hi>-chamber to his Majeſty, it had been one of the moſt honourable Places about his Perſon, as it is <hi>Groom of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> you may underſtand his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is to wait in the Guard-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to go of ſuch errands as any of the Gentlemen-Uſhers of the Preſence-chamber, nay, though they be but Quarter-waiters, ſhall think fit to employ him in. Now he had this Subtilty to make ſuch Readers as could not diſtinguiſh between Groom of the Chamber and Groom of the Bed-chamber believe he was ſome great Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, whereas in truth there is no ſuch matter, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e likely to take ſuch an employment, were he ſuch
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:55561:119"/>a proficient in Phyſick as he would have the world believe. I could ſhew the falſhood of moſt of thoſe Cures he pretends in that Book to have done, but that is not my task, who am already weary, but ſhall cloſe up all this diſcourſe with the words of Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> who ſpeaking of the great difficulties in the Art of Phyſick, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that perhaps, without preſumption, ſome innovation might be made in the <hi>Methodus Medendi,</hi> goes on: <hi>Yet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exper. Philoſ. p.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>pag.</hi> 202.</note> Pyro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus, <hi>I am much too young, too unlearned and too unexperienced to dare to be Dogmatical in a matter of ſo great moment. And the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians are a ſort of men, to whoſe learned Writings on almoſt all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects the Common-wealth of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is ſo much beholding, that I would not willingly diſſent from them about thoſe Notions in their own Profeſſion, wherein they ſeem generally to agree. And do very
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:55561:120"/>much diſapprove the indiſcreet pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of our common Chymiſts and</hi> Helmontians, <hi>that bitterly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcriminately rail at the Metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſts, in ſtead of candidly acquieſcing in theſe manifeſt Truths their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations have enrich'd us with, and civilly and modeſtly ſhewing them their errors where they have been miſtaken.</hi> Let me adviſe you hereafter, <hi>M. N.</hi> to write with ſuch modeſty and candor, as this both Learned and Honourable Perſon doth, and you will quickly learn to have a leſs eſteem for your ſelf, and the world put a greater value upon your Writings and Endeavours.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:55561:120"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. line 22. <hi>dele</hi> ſmattering. page 7. line 9. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>leg.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. page 21. in tit. <hi>dele</hi> all. page 23. in tit. <hi>leg.</hi> Natures appearances. page 25. line 8. <hi>leg.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>ib.</hi> line 20. <hi>leg.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. page 40. line 3. <hi>leg.</hi> could. page 33. tit. <hi>leg. M. N.</hi> confident aſſerting. page 56. line 15. <hi>leg.</hi> next. page 67. line 4. <hi>leg. popularis.</hi> page 70. line 4. after chapter adde <hi>is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> page 79. line 4. <hi>leg. doloſus.</hi> page 97. line 3. <hi>leg. Pharmacopaeas.</hi> page 103. line 23. <hi>leg. Pharmacopaeas.</hi> page 106. line 19. after <hi>therefore</hi> make a period, and let <hi>In</hi> begin a line. page 115. line ult. <hi>leg. Crat.</hi> page 145. line 6. <hi>leg.</hi> things. page 161. line 10. <hi>leg.</hi> which. page 166. line 16. after the word <hi>operations,</hi> adde <hi>and miſtake.</hi> page 169. line 22. <hi>leg.</hi> then I to ſay they are, &amp;c. page 189. line 20. <hi>leg. Leo Suavius.</hi> page 203. line 5. <hi>leg. Laboratory.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
